环球影片公司
康卡斯特旗下公司
环球 影业
出品
安培林 娱乐公司
制作
辛德勒的名单
本片真实地再现了德国企业家奥斯卡·辛德勒
在第二次世界大战期间保护1100余名犹太人免
遭法西斯杀害的真实的历史事件。
一九三九年九月
德国军队在两周内击败了波兰军队
犹太人被强迫登记所有亲属户口
并得搬迁到指定的大城市中
克拉科夫每天都涌入上万名犹太人
- Name?       - Horowitz, Salomon.
- 姓名？ - 所罗门•何洛维兹
- Over there. Over there!       - Come here!
- 过去那边排队    - 过这边来
- Isak Hudes.       - Hudes, Isak.
- 伊萨克•胡德斯    - 伊萨克•胡德斯
Zucker, Helena.
海莲娜•祖卡
Zucker, Helena!
Hirsch, Salomon?
所罗门•希尔施
- Hauptman, Chaim!       - Weisman! Weisman, Marcus!
- 汉恩•豪普曼    - 怀斯曼！马可士•怀斯曼
- Feber, Ludwig!       - Feber, Ludwig.
- 路德维克•法柏    - 路德维克•法柏
Elsa Bauman.
艾莎•鲍曼
- Josef Klein.       - Klein.
- 约瑟夫•科兰   - 科兰
- Davidowich, Ignacy.       - Paula Biffer.       - Nadel, Rachela.
- 伊科纳司•达维奇   - 宝拉•布菲   - 瑞琪拉•纳道
- Steiner, Gertruda.       - Steiner, Hilda.
- 古楚达•史坦纳    - 海达•史坦纳
- Jerzy, you know who that man is?       - I don't know.
- 贾斯  那个人是谁？  - 我也不知道
Let's get together, please.
麻烦靠近一点
Smile. Good!
笑一个  很好
已订位
Yes, sir.
是的  先生
Bring them over a round of drinks.
帮我送一瓶酒过去
Very good, sir. And who shall I say they are from?
好的  先生  请问要署名吗？
You can say they are from me.
就说是我送的就行了
- From the gentleman.       - Where?
- 是对面那位先生送的    - 哪位？
Do you know him?
你知道他是谁吗？
- Find out who he is.       - Yes, sir!
- 立刻去打听出来    - 是的  长官
Agnieszka, I would give anything to hear you sing tonight...
安姬妮丝卡  我今晚好想听你高歌一曲
...but I know you won't.
但我知道你不肯
You embarrass me.
您真让人难为情
What's he doing?
他在搞什么？
Stay here.
你待在这里
How are you doing?
你好啊
You'd leave a woman alone at the table in a place like this?
让这么漂亮的小姐在夜店落单  可不是个好主意呀
Sweetheart, you're the picture of loneliness.
甜心  你看起来好寂寞
What a lovely fragrance. You are breaking my heart.
真诱人的香水  你令我心碎
An extra chair, please. Vodka for my friend.
麻烦多拿一张椅子过来  给男士们来点伏特加
- And for the lady?       - Pernod!
- 那小姐要来点什么？ - 法国绿茴香酒
Come to the table, girls! Drink with us!
过来啊  小姑娘  陪我们喝酒
Come to us! Merry us!
嫁给我们吧
- Thank you.       - I'll tell you what I mean by cooperative.
- 谢谢    - 那些犹太人的奴性真强
Two days after the law is passed that all Jews have to wear the star...
犹太人必须穿戴臂章的法规  通过才不过两天的时间
...the Jewish tailors are turning them out by the gross in a variety...
那些犹太裁缝就已经做好了一堆各式款色的臂章
...of fabrics at three zloty each.
每个三元波币
Tell me about your cellar wines.
你店里有哪些好酒？
I have an excellent German Riesling, 1937.
我们有1937年份很棒的德国白酒
French! A Bordeaux. Chateau Latour, '28, '29?
有没有28或29年份法国拉图酒堡的波尔多红酒？
It's as if they have no idea what kind of law it is.
他们真是一点概念都没有
As if it's the emblem of a riding club.
简直是把那个臂章当作荣誉勋章来戴
- A Margaux, '29?       - No, no, we don't have that.
- 那29年的玛歌堡红酒呢？  - 抱歉  小店没有
- Burgundy then? A Romanee-Conti, '37?       - Yes.
- 那37年的罗曼尼康地红酒呢？ - 这个有
It's human nature.
那正是人性的弱点
"We'll do this to avoid that. "
"如果我们配合  或许他们会放了我们"
That's what they have done since thousands of years.
反正他们的文化背景就是如此  数千年来犹如过街老鼠
It's what they do. They weather the storm.
他们总是逆来顺受  以为有天会苦尽甘来
But this storm is different. This is not the Romans. This storm is the SS.
这次他们可是劫数难逃  罗马人可不比纳粹亲卫队
- Martin?       - Yes, sir!
- 马丁    - 是的  长官
Who is that man?
那个人是谁？
That's Oskar Schindler!
那是奥斯卡•辛德勒啊
犹太人参议会
由二十四名被推选出来的犹太人所组成
他们负责执行克拉科夫当局所发布的命令
诸如分配劳役、膳食、及住宿的分配
同时他们也负责排解纷争等问题
Private property cannot be confiscated.
不得任意没收私人财产…
- How long are the schools going to be closed?       - I do not know the answer..
- 学校还要关闭多久？ - 我不知道
- Article 47: Pillage is formally prohibited.       - You don't know anything!
- 第四十七条公约…    - 我看你什么都不知道
I am familiar with the Hague Convention.
他们并不在乎海牙公约
They come into our house and tell us we don't live there any more.
他们闯入我们家中  强迫我们搬走
It now belongs to a certain SS officer.
还说房子现在属于某位纳粹军官
Please! I only know what they tell me.
我只知道他们告诉我的那些事
And what they tell me changes from day to day!
而且他们朝令夕改
Aren't you supposed to be able to help?
难道你不应该帮助我们吗？
I mean, what if I just took this thing off?
要是我把臂章拿下
- What are they going to do about it?       - They will shoot you.
- 他们会怎么对付我？ - 他们会杀了你
- Why don't you stop this silly talk?       - Itzhak Stern!
- 你别在这里…    - 依札克•史登
I'm looking for Itzhak Stern.
我要找依札克•史登
Are you Itzhak Stern or not?
你到底是不是依札克•史登？
- I am.       - Where can we talk?
- 我是    - 可以借一步说话吗？
There's a company you did the books for, on Lipowa Street.
你以前帮立普瓦街上的一个工厂做过会计
Made what? Pots and pans?
他们是做什么来着？是做锅子的吗？
By law, I have to tell you, sir, I'm a Jew.
按照法律我必须先告诉你  我是犹太人
Well, I'm a German. So there we are.
很好  我是德国人  很高兴我们了解彼此
- A good company, you think?       - Modestly successful.
- 那是一家挺成功的公司  对吧？ - 还不错
I know nothing about enamelware. Do you?
我对搪瓷器皿可说是一无所知  那你呢？
I was just the accountant.
我只负责管钱
Simple engineering though, wouldn't you think?
不过原理应该很简单  你说是吧？
Change the machines around, whatever you do...
只要把机器调整一下
...you could make other things, couldn't you?
应该就可以生产其它东西
Field kits, mess kits. Army contracts.
例如一些军需生活用品  供给军队使用
Once the war ends, forget it, but for now it's great.
当然一旦战争结束就没用了  不过现在这可是很热门
You can make a fortune, don't you think?
应该可以大捞一笔  你说是吗？
I think most people right now have other priorities.
我想现在大家关心的应该不是这个
Like what?
那像是什么？
I'm sure you'll do just fine, once you get the contracts.
一旦你取得了军队合约后  相信一定生意兴隆
In fact, the worse things get, the better you'll do.
事实上  战争越惨烈  你赚得越多
Oh, well, I can get the signatures I need. That's the easy part.
取得军队的合约只是小事
Finding the money to buy the company, that's hard.
但是要找到买下工厂的资金  那才困难
You don't have any money?
你没有资金？
Not that kind of money. You know anybody?
我没有那么大笔的钱  你有认识什么人吗？
Jews, yeah.
像是一些犹太大金主
Investors. You must have contacts...
你在这里做事
...in the Jewish business community working here.
想必认识不少犹太金主
What community? Jews can no longer own businesses.
你搞错了  犹太人不能拥有任何私人产业
- That's why this one's in receivership.       - But they wouldn't own it.
- 所有犹太人的财物现在都被监管   - 公司不会登记在他们名下
I'd own it. I'd pay them back in product-pots and pans.
公司属于我  我会付给他们一些锅碗瓢盆做为报酬
- Pots and pans!       - Something they can use.
- 锅碗瓢盆    - 那些他们绝对用的着
Something they can feel in their hands.
可以握在手中的真实东西
They can trade it on the black market, do whatever they want.
甚至可以拿去黑市交换  用处可大了
Everybody's happy!
大家各取所需
If you want, you could run the company for me.
如果你愿意  你可以帮我管理这个工厂
Let me understand.
让我确定我没听错
They'd put up all the money, I'd do all the work.
他们出全部的钱  我做全部的工作
What, if you don't mind my asking, would you do?
如果你不介意我这么问  那你要做什么？
I'd make sure it's known the company's in business.
我会让大家都知道这个工厂的存在
I'd see that it had a certain panache.
把工厂搞得声名大噪
That's what I'm good at. Not the work, not the work.
我擅长的是公关  不是工作
The presentation!
我是做表面功夫的
I'm sure I don't know anybody who'll be interested in this.
我确定我不认识任何会对这个主意感兴趣的人
Well, they should be, Itzhak Stern.
他们应该再考虑看看  依札克•史登
Tell them they should be.
告诉他们  他们应该抓住这个机会
I've got a client who'll sell marks for zloty at 2.45 to 1.
我有一个顾客愿意用2.45马克兑换一块波币
Wool, mink collar. It's a nice coat.
纯羊毛  加上貂皮领子  那是一件上好的大衣
She'll trade it for ration coupons.
她愿意用大衣换粮票
- Wicks, for lamps.       - You have a truckload of wicks?
- 油灯的灯芯    - 你有一卡车油灯的灯芯？
What am I going to do with a truckload of wicks?
我要一卡车油灯的灯芯干嘛？
9 by 12, 9 by 14.
九寸乘十二寸  还是十四寸的
I don't know. Big, beautiful, Persian.
又大又漂亮的波斯地毯
- What?       - You don't recognize this?
- 干嘛？ - 你认得这个东西吗？
- It's shoe polish.       - In metal containers?
- 这是鞋油    - 我要的是铁盒装的鞋油
You asked for shoe polish.
鞋油就是鞋油
In metal containers. This is glass, it's not what I asked for.
我要的是铁盒装的鞋油  不是玻璃瓶装的
What's the difference?
那有什么差别？
- What's the difference?       - What's the difference?
- 那有什么差别？ - 那有什么差别？
My client sold it to his client, who sold it to the German Army.
我的买主把这个卖给他的买主  然后再转卖给军队
Only by the time it got there, because of the freezing cold, it broke.
可惜货运到的时候  因为天寒地冻  这些瓶子都裂了
All 10,000 units.
总共损失一万瓶鞋油
This is not my problem.
那不是我的问题
- This is not his problem.       - This is not your problem?
- 那不是他的问题    - 那不是你的问题？
- This is not my problem.       - All right!
- 那不是我的问题    - 好吧
The German Army wants to find out where it came from.
现在德国军队想要找出这批货来自何方
- I am going to make sure they find out.       - Now it's your problem.
- 我会叫他们直接来找你    - 现在这可是你的问题了
You be quiet!
你闭嘴
Metal containers.
铁盒装的鞋油
Hello!
你们好
Pardon me for interfering, but that's a nice shirt.
很抱歉打扰你们  但是我很欣赏你的衬衫
Nice shirt.
非常漂亮的衬衫
Do you know where I can find a nice shirt like that?
你知道我要到哪去找这么漂亮的衬衫吗？
Like this?
像我身上的这件？
It's illegal to buy or sell anything on the street.
在街上买卖东西是违法的
We don't do that. We're here to pray.
我们不做这种违法的事  我们是来这里祷告的
Do you have any idea how much a shirt like this costs?
你知道这种衬衫要值多少钱吗？
Nice things cost money.
那自然是一分钱一分货
How many?
你要几件？
I'm going to need some other things, too, as things come up.
我以后可能还会需要一些别的
- This won't be a problem.       - From time to time.
- 没问题    - 到时再告诉你
一九四一年三月二十日
强制迁入犹太区的最后期限
44/91号公告：在维斯拉河以南强制建立了一个封闭式的犹太社区
高墙围绕的社区内住宅实行配给制
所有来自克拉科夫和邻近城市的犹太人
被迫放弃家园并移居到这个只有十六个街区大的社区内
This is obviously the right place. How are you doing?
真是来对了地方  你好啊
Goodbye, Jews! Goodbye, Jews!
再见啦  犹太人
犹太人快滚吧
Oh, my God!
天啊
Oy, God! Oh, my God!
天啊  我的天啊
Oh, my God!
天啊
It could not be better.
再没有比这里更棒的了
- It could be worse.       - How? Tell me.
- 要庆幸没有比这更糟糕    - 这已经够糟糕了
How on earth could it possibly be worse?
怎么可能有比这更糟的？
Good morning!
你们好
- Hey, Goldberg.       - Poldek.
- 嗨  古柏特    - 波利克
- What's this?       - Uh, the Jewis assembly has its own police now.
- 这是什么？ - 我们犹太委员会有自己的警察
- You don't say.       - Coordination service!
- 真的假的？  - 犹太保安警察
I'm a policeman now, could you believe it? It's hard to believe.
我现在可是警察了  很难相信吧？
Oh, no, it's not hard to believe.
我相信
It's a good racket, Poldek. The only racket here.
待遇很不错的  这是这里唯一合法的差事
Look, maybe I could put in a good word for you with my superiors.
也许我可以向我的上级推荐你
- Your superiors?       - Come on, they're not as bad as everyone says.
- 你的上级？ - 别这样  他们不像别人说得那么坏
Well, they're worse than everyone says, but it's a lot of money.
其实他们比那更坏  但是待遇真的很好
A lot of money!
薪水很高的
Give me my housing assignment.
把我的指定地址给我
- Come on.       - You look funny in that hat, Goldberg.
- 快给啊    - 你戴的那顶帽子真可笑  古柏特
You look like a clown, you know?
你看起来好像小丑
He's a very important man.
他是个大人物
Just give him two minutes of your time.
你们只要给他几分钟的时间就好
Since when did time cost money? Just sit down and listen...
反正你们闲着也没事  就坐下来聊聊
...please! Sir?
先生
For each thousand you invest, I will repay you with...
你们每投资一千元  我会付给你们…
- Two hundred.       - ... 200 kilos of enamelware a month...
- 两百    - 每个月两百公斤的搪瓷器皿
...to begin in July and to continue for one year.
从七月开始维持一年的时间
After which time, we're even. That's it. It's very simple.
之后我们就算扯平了  就是这样  非常简单
- Not good enough.       - It's not good enough!
- 这条件不够好    - 条件不够好
Not good enough?
不够好？
Look where you're living. Look where you've been put. "Not good enough! "
看看你们住的地方  看看你们的周围  "条件不够好"？
A couple of months ago you'd be right, not anymore.
几个月前或许你们还能这么说  现在可不行了
Money's still money.
但是钱还是钱
No, it is not! That's why we are here.
不  不再是了  这就是我们今天要谈的
Trade goods that's the only currency that'll be worth anything in the ghetto.
在犹太区现金是没用的  以物易物才是生存的法则
Things have changed, my friend.
现在情况已经不一样了  我的朋友
Did I call this meeting?
是我约你们来谈生意的吗？
You told Mr Stern you wanted to speak to me.
是你们自己拜托史登先生来约我的
I'm here. I've made you a fair offer.
现在我来了  也给了你们公平的条件
Fair would be a percentage in the company.
要是公平的话  你就该给我们公司的股份
Forget the whole thing. Get out!
那就拉倒  你们请吧
How do we know that you will do what you say?
我们怎么知道你会信守承诺？
Because I said I would.
因为我说我会
You want a contract? To be upheld by what court?
你们想要合约吗？还是想去法院公证？
I said what I'll do. That's our contract.
我说我会做到  那就是我们之间的约定
Five, six, seven, eight, nine...
五 六 七 八 九...
The standard SS rate for Jewish skilled labourers is seven marks a day...
纳粹政府规定给犹太专业工人一天七块马克的工资
...five for unskilled and women.
非专业及女性犹太工人则是五块
This is what you pay the Reich Economic Office.
你把工资直接交给纳粹德国的经济部门
The Jews themselves receive nothing.
犹太工人本身则领不到任何酬劳
Poles you pay wages. Generally, they get a little more.
波兰工人可直接向工厂领薪水  他们的工资也比较高
- Are you listening?       - What was that about the SS?
- 你有在听吗？ - 你刚才说纳粹政府什么来着？
The rate? The what?
关于工资的那段
The Jewish worker's salary, you pay it directly to the SS, not to the worker.
犹太工人的薪水你直接付给政府  你不用付钱给工人
- He gets nothing.       - But it's less.
- 他们一毛也拿不到    - 但是他们比较便宜
- It's less than what I would pay a Pole.       - It's less?
- 他们比波兰工人便宜    - 是比较便宜
That's the point I'm trying to make.
这才是重点
Poles cost more.
波兰人比较贵
Why should I hire Poles?
那我干嘛要请波兰人？
An enamelware factory, over at, Lipowa Street.
那是一家在立普瓦街上的搪瓷器皿工厂
It, uh, it, um... It's owned by a German.
老板是一个德国人
But it's outside the ghetto, so you can barter for extra goods...
但是那在犹太区外  所以你们会有机会
...for eggs, I don't know what you need...
和波兰工人去交换你们需要的东西
...with the Polish workers. You can't get it here.
那在犹太区中是不可能的
Also, he's asking for ten healthy women for the...
还有  他也要找十个健康的女人
I'm healthy!
我也很健康啊
Bring your sister, okay?
还是叫你妹妹来吧
You need to convince them you have a trade, something valuable to the war effort.
你必须说服他们你有特殊技能  能对战争作出贡献
- Like what?       - I'm a musician.       - What if you don't?
- 像是什么？ - 我是音乐家     - 要是没有技能怎么办？
- Your name goes on a list.       - Your name is on the list, they put you on trucks...
- 你的名字就会被放在名单上    - 然后你就会被赶上卡车…
- No, no, no, that's not true.       - You're a musician?
- 不  不会的      - 你是个音乐家？
- Yeah.       - I'd find a good hiding place if I were you.
- 是啊    - 我要是你  我会去找个藏身之处
- I'm not going to hide like some animal.       - There are places to hide.
- 我才不要像个畜生般的藏起来    - 其实有很多地方可藏
The next!
下一个
I'm a graduate of the University of Lwow.
我是里沃夫大学毕业的
I used to work at the hydroelectric station in Roznow...
我以前在水力发电厂工作…
Blue card!
蓝卡
I'm gonna get the necessary papers because this card is no good any more.
我会去帮你准备文件  因为你这张卡一点用也没有
You can stay in this line all day, you'll still get one of these.
就算你在这等上一天  你还是会拿到同一张卡
They are no good. You'll have to leave the line now...
这张没有用  你不要再排队了
...then you'll get a blue card, a Blauschein, to say that you are an essential worker.
你需要一张蓝卡  那代表你是有重要技能的工人
I'll get these papers for you at Pankiewicz.
我会帮你在潘克维兹那里取得这些证明文件
Pharmacist. Just there, look!
你看  就是那个药剂师那里
Guess who is here?
看看是谁来了
Poldek! Enjoying the weather, Poldek?
波利克  你那边天气如何？
- Enjoying the lines?       - Need some shoe polish?
- 看你排队排得很高兴嘛    - 要不要买鞋油啊？
In metal container maybe!
是铁盒装的哦
Not essential? I think you misunderstand the meaning of the word.
没有重要技能？我想你误解重要的意义了
No blue card, sir. Stand over there.
你不能取得蓝卡  请走开
Move. Next!
下一个
What do you mean, "Not essential"?
什么叫没有重要技能？
I teach history and literature. Since when it's not essential?
我是历史和文学老师  这难道不算是重要技能？
He's metal polisher.
他是金属打磨师
- It was not right?       - It's very good. He's 53 years old.
- 我弄错了吗？ - 是太完美了  他今年53岁
- It's too new.       - Thank you.
- 这文件看起来太新了    - 谢谢你
You're crazy. You left it in your drawer.
你真蠢  竟然把文件丢在抽屉里
How many times have I told you?
都跟你说了几次了？
Your work certificate, you keep in your pocket at all times.
你的工作文件得随时随身带着
And you leave everything in your drawer.
绝对不能乱丢在抽屉里
How many times I've told you?
我跟你说了几次了？
I'm a metal polisher!
我是金属打磨师
Take the round sheet of tin...
拿着这张圆型的锡板
...dip it in soap emulsion.
把它浸在肥皂乳中
Then place it centrally in the press.
然后放在模子的正中间
We obtain the soup pot. The soup pot!
这就成了一个汤锅
Soup pot!
汤锅
Grosz, Mrs Grosz, stay together.
葛兹夫妇  麻烦跟紧一点
Look, sir, I have ten work permits here for the German enamel factory...
长官  我这里有十张德意志搪瓷器皿工厂核发的工作证
...and signed by Mr Bankier and myself.
上面有班克耶先生和我的签名
If it's carbonized, clean it with a file.
如果表面被碳化  就用锉刀把它磨干净
But don't touch both the electrodes at the same time.
小心不要同时触碰两个电极
You'll get electrocuted. Here, have a try.
你会被电到  来  你试试看
Roll the metal under the press...
把金属放到模子底下
...but be very careful unless you want your fingers...
但是要小心自己的手指
...to become part of the teapot!
不要变成茶壶的一部份了
- Occupation?       - I'm a writer. I play the flute.
- 职业？  - 我是个作家  我也会吹长笛
But Moses is a skilled metalworker.
但是摩西也是个专业的金属工人
He can make tin pots. He can make tanks.
他会做锡锅  也会做坦克车
He can make whatever Mr Schindler asks.
只要是辛德勒先生要的  他都能做得出来
He's highly skilled. Give him your card.
他有高级技能  把你的卡给他
Moses, give him your card.
摩西  把你的卡给他
Now, dip the basin with the tongs into the enamel solution.
现在  用夹子把脸盆浸在搪瓷溶液中
And after swiveling it around, carefully place it aside to drip-dry.
然后轻轻地转一转  再小心地放在旁边晾干
And whatever he asks you, allow me just to represent you and speak for you.
不管他问你什么  都让我代表你回答
Don't say a word!
你什么都别说
Filing, billing, keeping track of my appointments, shorthand.
建档、报帐、掌管行事历、速记
- Typing, obviously. How is your typing?       - Uh, all right.
- 当然还要打字  你的打字速度如何？ - 还可以
Please!
请试试
You need a secretary. Pick one.
你需要一个秘书  你就挑一个吧
I don't know how. They're all so... qualified.
我挑不出来  她们都很称职
You have to choose.
你非得做个选择
Big smile, big smile!
笑一个  笑一个
If you would, look after my guest.
请帮我好好招呼我的客人
Um, boxed teas are good. Coffee, puum...
上等的盒装茶叶  咖啡  鹅肝酱
...kielbasa sausage, cheeses, Beluga caviar...
波兰熏肠、起司、贝露加鱼子酱
...and, of course, who could live without German cigarettes?
还有德国香烟是绝对不能少的
Get me as many as you can find.
能弄到多少就要多少
And some more fresh fruit.
还要新鲜的水果
The real rarities, oranges, lemons, pineapples.
稀有的热带水果…柳橙、柠檬、凤梨
I need several boxes of Cuban cigars. The best.
我还要几盒最好的古巴雪茄
And dark unsweetened chocolate...
还有不加糖的黑巧克力
...not in the shape of ladyfingers, the chunk chocolate.
不要一条一条的那种  要那种一大块的
Big as my hand, you sample at wine tastings.
要像拳头那么大  品酒的时候吃的那种
We're going to need lots of cognac. The best, Hennessy.
还需要很多的干邑白兰地  要轩尼诗的
Dom Perignon champagne. Um, get L 'espadon sardines...
香槟王的香槟  顶级沙丁鱼罐头
...and, oh, try to find nylon stockings.
再帮我找找女人的尼龙丝袜
It is my distinct pleasure to announce...
我很荣幸地向您宣布
...the fully operational status of German enamel factory...
德意志搪瓷器皿工厂已全面正式开工
...manufacturers of superior enamelware crockery...
本工厂专门生产各类特别为军队需要…
...expressly designed and crafted for military use.
所设计的高级搪瓷器皿
Utilizing only the most modern equipment...
本工厂使用最先进的仪器设备
...D.E.F.'s staff of highly skilled and experienced artisans and journeymen...
德意志工厂拥有最精良的工匠及最优秀的技师
...deliver a product of unparalleled quality...
为您制造品质无可比拟的产品
...enabling me to proffer, with absolute confidence and pride...
我在此诚挚的为您呈献
...a full line of field and kitchenware...
全系列的军旅及军炊用品
...unsurpassable in all respects by my competitors.
其质量远超过其他厂商所能提供
See attached list and available colours.
所有颜色款式请参考所附的资料表
Anticipating the enclosed bids will meet with your approval...
相信我们所投标的价钱能获得您的首肯
...looking forward to a long and mutually prosperous association...
期望与您共创一个长久互惠的合作关系
...I extend to you in advance my sincerest gratitude...
我先行向您表达我诚挚的谢意
...and very best regards. Oskar Schindler.
并祝一切安好  奥斯卡•辛德勒敬上
Yeah, I need 700 gross from here for next Thursday.
下个星期四之前  我需要七百件成品
Nine hundred, no, make it ten for Wednesday.
九百个…  不  下星期三前我们得要一千件
All this stuff here goes to Madritsch's factory on Tuesday of next week.
下个星期二之前  把这些都运去马得区的工厂
My father was fond of saying, "You need three things in life... "
我父亲以前常说  人生之中你需要三样东西
"... a good doctor, a forgiving priest... "
一个好医生  一个宽容的牧师
"... and a clever accountant. "
和一个精明的会计
The first two, I've never had much use for.
前面两者我总是派不上用场
But the third!
但是这第三个…
Just pretend, for Christ's sake!
你难道不能假装一下
Is that all?
还有别的事吗？
I'm trying to thank you.
我是在感谢你呀
I'm saying I couldn't have done this without you.
我是说  没有你就不会有今天的这番局面
The usual thing would be to acknowledge my gratitude.
一般来说  你应该要回应个几句客套话
It would also, by the way, be the courteous thing.
这才是应有的礼仪
You're welcome.
不客气
Get out of here!
你滚吧
Klonowska, who is it?
克诺丝卡  是谁啊？
She's so embarrassed. Look at her.
你看看她  她真的很困窘
You know something? You would like her.
你知道吗？你一定会喜欢她的
- Oskar, please!       - What?
- 奥斯卡  别这样    - 怎样？
I don't have to like her... just because you do.
只因为你很喜欢她  不表示我也得喜欢她
It doesn't work that way.
事情不该是这样的
You've done well here.
看来你生意做得不错
You look wonderful.
你看来美极了
- Be careful of the step, miss.       - Mrs Schindler, Marek.
- 小心台阶  小姐    - 是辛德勒夫人  马瑞克
- It's not a charade, all this?       - Charade? How could it be a charade?
- 这一切不会只是假象吧？  - 这怎么可能只是假象？
- The clothes, the car, the apartment.       - Wait a minute.
- 你有了车  还有洋房    - 等等
Take a guess how many people are on my payroll.
猜猜我工厂总共有多少员工
Oskar!
奥斯卡
My father, at the height of his success, had 50. I've got 350.
我父亲在他事业最成功时不过有50个员工  我现在有350个
350 workers on the factory floor, with one purpose.
我工厂里的350个员工只有一个共同目标
To make pots and pans?
是制造锅碗瓢盆吗？
To make money. For me!
是赚钱  替我赚钱
Does anyone ask about me?
有人问起我吗？
Back home? Everybody. All the time.
在家乡？大家每天都问
They won't soon forget the name Schindler here, I can tell you that.
至少我可以肯定 在这里人们永远不会忘了我
"Oskar Schindler" they'll say.
他们会说  那个奥斯卡•辛德勒
"Everybody remembers him. "
大家都记得他
"He did something extraordinary. "
他成就了非凡的事业
"He did something no one else did. "
他为人所不能为
"He came here with nothing, a suitcase...
他初来时一无所有  只有一只皮箱
"... and built a bankrupt company into a major manufactory. "
他把一间破产的公司改造成一家首屈一指的制造工厂
"And left with a steamer trunk... "
他离去时  带着整整一箱…
"... two steamer trunks full of money. "
两大箱的钞票
"All the riches of the world. "
享不尽的荣华富贵
It's comforting to see that nothing's changed.
很高兴看到一切还是没变
You're wrong, Emilie.
你错了  艾蜜莉
There's no way I could have known this before but...
我以前从来都不可能知道
...there was always something missing.
但是我一直缺了一些东西
In every business I tried, I can see now, it wasn't me that failed.
我现在懂了  我所尝试的每个生意失败的原因并不是我
Something was missing.
我一直缺了一些东西
Even if I'd known what it was, there's nothing I could have done about it...
就算当时我知道是什么  我也束手无策
...because you can't create this thing.
因为有的东西是你不能创造的
And it makes all the difference in the world between success and failure.
这东西决定了所有世间的成败
Luck?
那是运气吗？
War!
是战争
Should I stay?
我该留下来吗？
It's a beautiful city.
这是个美丽的城市
I asked you if I should stay.
我是问你我是否该留下
It's up to you.
我尊重你的决定
Promise me, Oskar. No doorman or maitre d' will ever presume...
答应我  奥斯卡  不要再有任何门房或领班...
...I'm anyone other than Mrs. Schindler, and I'll stay.
认为我不是独一无二的辛德勒夫人  那么我就愿意留下
Goodbye, darling.
再见吧  亲爱的
再见  保重
I could try to read this or I could eat my lunch while it's still hot.
我可以选择读帐本  或者是趁热吃我的午餐
We're doing well?
我们的生意兴隆吗？
- Yes.       - Better this month than last?
- 是的  - 这个月比上个月赚了更多钱？
- Yes.       - Any reason to think next month will be worse?
- 是的  - 有任何理由认为下个月会亏损吗？
The war could end.
战争有可能会结束
- What?       - There is a machinist outside...
- 干嘛？  - 外面有一位工厂工人
...who'd like to thank you personally for giving him a job.
想要亲自感谢你给他一份工作
Every day he comes. He's very grateful. It'll just take a minute.
他每天都来等  非常热忱  不会耽误很多时间的
Mr Lowenstein!
罗温斯坦先生
I want to thank you, sir, for giving me the opportunity to work.
我想要感谢您给了我一个工作的机会
You're welcome. I'm sure you're doing a great job.
不客气  我相信你一定表现杰出
The SS beat me up. They would have killed me...
那些纳粹亲卫队把我打得半死  他们本来要杀了我的
...but I am essential to the war effort, thanks to you.
还好我是您这里的重要技工
That's great.
那真是太好了
I work hard for you.
我非常努力的工作
- I'm sure you do.       - I'll continue to work hard for you.
- 我知道    - 我会继续努力工作报答您
That's great. Thanks.
很好  谢谢你
- God bless you, sir.       - All right.
- 愿神保佑您  先生    - 很好
You are a good man.
您是个好人
- He saved my life.       - Yes, he did.
- 他救了我的命    - 没错
- God bless him.       - Yeah. Come on.
- 愿神保佑他   - 是的  走吧
God bless you!
愿神保佑您
I'm sorry, Herr Direktor, but you're running very late.
我很抱歉  厂长先生  但是你已经要迟到了
This is for the major, sir.
这个是要送给中尉的
And this is for his niece, Greta. It's her birthday.
这个是要给他的侄女葛蕾塔的  今天是她的生日
Don't ever do that to me again.
你以后别再这样耍我了
Go. Go, go, drive! Don't bow.
快去开车啊  发什么呆？
- Did you notice that man had one arm?       - Did he?
- 难道你没注意到他只有一只手？ - 真的吗？
- What's his use?       - Very useful.
- 他是哪门子的技工？ - 非常重要的
- How?       - Very useful! Success!
- 怎么可能？ - 非常重要  加油啊
You'll be given brooms and shovels...
我们会发给你们扫帚和铁铲
...each of you will grab one and start cleaning the street.
每个人都要拿一样开始清理街道
We'll be late for work.
我们上班会迟到的
You shouldn't think of them as yours, Oskar.
你不该把他们看成你的所有物  奥斯卡
You need to understand that some of the officers here...
你必须了解  这里有的军官
...don't give a damn about production.
并不在乎工厂的进度
To them, it's a matter of, um, national priority...
对他们而言  强迫犹太人铲雪
...that Jews be made to shovel snow.
是这个国家最为重要的事之一
It's got nothing to do with reality, Oskar.
这跟现实完全无关  奥斯卡
You know it and I know it.
你我都知道
Jews shoveling snow!
犹太人铲雪…
It's got a, um, ritual significance.
有其象征性的意义
- Come with me.       - I am an essential worker.
- 跟我们来    - 我是重要的技工
- Essential worker?       - Yes.
- 重要的技工？ - 是的
- I work for Oskar Schindler.       - Essential worker for Oskar Schindler.
- 我替奥斯卡•辛德勒做事    - 奥斯卡•辛德勒的重要技工
A one-armed Jew? Twice as useless!
一个独臂的犹太人更不应该活在世界上
I lost a day of production, Rolf.
我整整失去了工厂一天的生产量  罗夫
I work for Oskar Schindler.
我替奥斯卡•辛德勒做工
Danka, look at the snow. Look at the snow. Look at the snow!
丹卡  低头看着雪  低头看着雪
I lost a worker. I expect to be compensated.
我失去了一个工人  我必须获得赔偿
File a grievance with the Economic Office. It's your right.
你可以去跟经济部申请  那是你的权益
- Would it do any good?       - Of course not!
- 那会有用吗？ - 当然不会
A big shot from the SS Budget and Construction Office came to lunch...
一位财政建设部门的纳粹高官来这里用午餐时告诉我们
...and he told us that to believe the Jewish skilled worker had a place...
如果有人认为犹太技工能在纳粹德国的经济体系中占有一席之地
...in Reich economics was a treasonable idea.
那是一种叛国的思想
A one-armed machinist, Oskar?
一个独臂的工人  奥斯卡？
He was a metal press operator.
他负责操作金属模具
Quite skilled.
非常资深
Mr. Director!
厂长先生
Shit. I don't believe it.
该死  搞什么鬼？
Stern, is that you?
史登  是你吗？
No, it's Poldek. It's about Stern.
不  我是波利克  史登出事了
Leave your luggage on the platform.
请把行李留在月台上
Clearly label it.
并清楚地贴上标签
Given name first, then your surname.
写好姓名
Do not bring your baggage with you.
请不要携带你的行李上火车
It will follow you later.
行李随后会分开运到
Leave your luggage on the platform.
请把行李留在月台上
Clearly label it.
并清楚地贴上标签
Leave your luggage on the platform.
请把行李留在月台上
Stern?
史登
- He's on the list.       - He is?
- 他在名单上    - 是吗？
- Well, let's find him.       - I'm sorry. You can't have him.
- 赶快把他找出来    - 很抱歉  你不能带他走
He's on the list. If he were an essential worker, he would not be on the list.
他在名单上  如果他真的是重要技工  他是不会在名单上的
I'm talking to a clerk. What is your name?
我干嘛跟一个小书记啰唆  你叫什么名字？
- Sir, the list is correct.       - I didn't ask you about the list.
- 先生  这个名单是正确的    - 我没有问你名单是否正确
- I asked you your name.       - Klaus Tauber.
- 我问的是你的名字    - 克劳斯•塔柏
Tauber!
塔柏
Squad leader, this gentleman thinks a mistake's been made.
士官长  这位先生认为我们的名单出了问题
My plant manager is somewhere on this train.
我的工厂经理在你们的火车上
If it leaves with him on it, it'll disrupt production...
要是火车开跑了  那可会严重影响工厂产量
...and the Armaments Board will want to know why.
到时候军备部门肯定会怪罪下来
- Attention! The train is about to leave.       - Is he on the list?
- 注意！火车就要开了    - 他在名单上吗？
Yes, sir. Itzhak Stern.
是的  长官  依札克•史登
Well, the list is correct, sir. There is nothing I can do.
这份名单正确无误  先生  我们没有办法通融
- What is your name?       - Close and secure all doors.
- 你叫什么名字？ - 关紧所有门窗
- My name? My name is Kunder.       - This train is now leaving.
- 我的名字？我的名字是昆德    - 火车就要开了
- Kunder.       - Hauptscharfurer Kunder.
- 昆德    - 昆德士官长
- K-U-N-D-E-R.       - And what's yours?
- K-U-N-D-E-R    - 而你的大名是？
Schindler. S-C-H-I-N-D-L-E-R.
辛德勒
Gentlemen, thank you very much.
谢谢两位
I think I can guarantee you you'll both be in...
我可以向你们保证  在月底之前...
...Southern Russia before the end of the month. Good day.
你们一定会被发配到南俄去  祝您愉快
Stern!
史登
- Stern!       - Stern!
- 史登   - 史登
Itzhak Stern!
依札克•史登
Stern! Itzhak Stern!
史登  依札克•史登
- Stern! Stern!       - Itzhak Stern!
- 史登    - 依札克•史登
- Stern!       - Sir!
- 史登   - 先生？
- Stern!       - Herr Direktor!
- 史登    - 厂长先生
My apologies.
我很抱歉
- Stop the train! He's here!       - I apologize.
- 把火车停下  他在这里    - 真对不起
- Stop the train!       - Stop the train! Stop it!
- 快把火车停下    - 把火车停下来
Sign here. Initial there.
请在这里签个名
Makes no difference to us, you understand. This one, that one.
反正对我们没什么差别  抓别人也是一样的
It's the inconvenience to the list.
名单的缺点就是很死板
- It's the paperwork.       - I somehow left my work card at home.
- 毕竟是白纸黑字的文件    - 我把工卡忘在家里了
I tried to explain them it was a mistake, but...
我试着跟他们解释  说这是一个误会…
- ... I'm sorry, it was stupid!       - What if I got here five minutes later?
- 对不起  我真蠢    - 要是我晚五分钟才到呢？
Then where would I be?
那我得上哪儿去找你？
■
车站货仓里,工人们正在挑拣着堆积如山的货物给其分类,这些都是火车上被
运走的犹太人的,当然,这些对于它们的主人来说已经没用了,因为他们踏上的
是一辆死亡列车,即将开往屠宰场...一名黄金鉴定师望着倒在桌上的一大堆
金牙,面色呆滞,因为他知道,一颗金牙代表着一个生命的终结...
“犹太人城”
一九四二年冬 克拉科夫犹太人区
（波兰人与波兰犹太人这时已经被明确的化分开来）
I woke up from a dream this morning.
我昨晚做了一个梦
I was broke and sharing a room with 12 people I didn't know...
梦到我身无分文  并跟12个陌生人挤在一个小房间里
...only to discover I was broke and sharing a room with 12 people I didn't know.
一觉醒来发现自己的处境和梦中的真是一模一样
- You laugh about it?       - I have to laugh.
- 你觉得这很好笑？ - 不笑又能如何
You are living behind walls.
我们被拘禁在高墙之后
The walls I can deal with. It's the restrictions to my life I'm tired of.
我不在意这些墙  我在意的是那些遵守不完的规则
Those walls keep them out. That's all I care about.
多亏了那些墙  把那些充满敌意的人阻隔在外面
I like it here. There's a kind of, I don't know...
我喜欢这里  我也说不上来为什么
...ancestral squalor to it all.
我觉得我们跟老祖先一样在奋斗
- You are a slave to these people.       - No one envies us any more.
- 你是那些人的奴才    - 我们再也不是众人羡慕的对象
- I'm smart!       - Oh, yes, you're smart!
- 识时务者为俊杰    - 是啊  就属你最识相
- You're a real genius.       - You had your chance.
- 你真是个天才    - 是你自己选择放弃的
Today, today I actually found time to organize a thought.
我今天竟然有闲暇时间整理我自己的思绪
I can't remember the last time I did that.
我甚至不记得上次这样做是什么时候
When's the last time we did this?
我们上次这样做是什么时候？
When's the last time we stood around and talked?
我们上次一起闲聊是什么时候？
No one ordered me onto a truck today.
至少今天没有人把我赶上卡车
No one took my business away from me.
也没有人抢走我的生意
You don't really have a business to take.
你已经没有生意好抢了
There's nowhere down from here.
至少不可能比这样更糟了
This is it. This is the bottom.
这一定已经是最糟的情况
The ghetto is, liberty!
至少我们在犹太区中享有自由
This street divides the ghetto just about in half.
这条街将犹太区一分为二
Right side, Ghetto A: Civil employees industrial workers and so on.
右边是犹太A区  住的是公职人员和工业人员
Left side, Ghetto B: Surplus labour... the elderly and infirm mostly.
左边是犹太B区  住的是备用工人及老弱妇孺
Which is where you'll want to start, huh?
我们应该先从哪里开始清理？
阿蒙葛斯少尉（精卫队司令,生性残暴,亲手杀掉了500多个犹太人）
Do you have any questions, sir?
您有任何问题吗  长官？
Ja, why is the top down? I'm fucking freezing.
有  为什么不把车篷关上？我快要冻死了
We expect a labor force of 25.000 to 30.000.
我们预计会有将近三万名的劳工
正在赶建中的普拉邵强制劳动营
Segregated of course. The men in the barracks near the guarry...
男女分开来管理  男的就住在矿场附近的营房
- ... the women on the other side of the wire.       - My place is where?
- 女的安置在…      - 那我住在哪儿？
- There, sir.       - There?
- 那里  长官     - 就那里？
- Yes, the villa.       - You call that a villa?
- 是的  那栋别墅    - 那个也叫别墅？
- Their synagogue, can you see it?       - That's not a villa!
- 那是他们的教堂    - 那个称不上是别墅
- We' to turn it into the camp stables.       - It's a house!
- 我们打算把它改建成马房    - 充其量算是栋房子
What's that over there?
那个又是什么？
Playground. Fifty-one.
幼稚园
And we have a dentist, shoemaker, practical physicians.
我们有一个牙医  一个鞋匠和几个医生
There they are, sir.
她们来了
One of you is, uh, a very lucky girl.
你们当中即将出现一个幸运的女孩
There is an opening for a job...
我们现在有一个职务空缺
...away from all this, backbreaking work...
被选中的人将不再从事一般的苦工
...at my new villa.
并能搬入我的新别墅中
...which of you has domestic experience?
你们当中有谁有过帮佣的经验？
Yeah, on second thought, I don't really want someone else's maid.
不过话又说回来  我不想捡别人用过的女佣
All those annoying habits I have to undo.
做惯女佣的人通常有一堆坏习惯
I don't want to give you my cold.
我不想把感冒传染给你
Uh, what's your name?
你叫什么名字？
- Helen Hirsch.       - What?
- 海伦•希尔施     - 什么？
Helen Hirsch.
海伦•希尔施
- What? I can't hear.       - Helen Hirsch.
- 什么？我听不见    - 海伦•希尔施
- Yes!       - Take it all down!
- 就用她    - 把这里拆了
- Back to your work!       - To work!
- 回去工作吧    - 工作
Take it down! It is not safe!
这些都得拆了  这里不安全
She says the foundation was poured wrong. She's got to take it down.
她说我们地基灌浆出了问题  得把这里拆了重盖
I told her it's the barracks, not the fucking Hotel Europa.
我告诉她这里只是营房  不是什么五星级大饭店
Fucking Jew bitch engineer. You fucking bitch!
该死的犹太工程师母狗  你这该死的母狗
Herr Kommandant. The entire foundation has to be torn down and repoured.
指挥官大人  这里的整个地基都得打掉重灌
If not, there will be at least a subsidence...
如果不这样做  地基会塌陷
...at the southern end of the barracks.
先从营房的南边开始
Subsidence, and then collapse.
接下来整个营房都会倒塌
- And you are an engineer?       - Yes!
- 你是工程师？ - 是的
My name is Diana Reiter. I'm a graduate...
我的名字是黛安娜•莱特
...of Civil Engineering from the University of Milan.
我是米兰大学工程系的毕业生
Ah, an educated Jew, like Karl Marx himself.
一个受过教育的犹太人  就像卡尔•马克思
- Sergeant!       - Yes, sir!
- 士官   - 是的  长官
- Shoot her.       - What?
- 杀了她     - 什么？
Commander! I'm only trying to do my job.
指挥官大人  我只是做我份内的事
Yeah, I'm doing mine.
我也是
Sir, she's foreman of construction.
但是长官  她是这里的工头
We are not going to have arguments with these people.
我们不能受到这些人的胁迫
Okay!
是的
No! Shoot her here, on my authority!
不  我要你把她就地正法
- It will take more than that.       - I'm sure, you are right!
- 我说的都是真的啊    - 我知道
Take it down, repour it, rebuild it. Like she said.
把这里拆了  重新灌浆  照她说的做
We have more to see, but we have only one more hour of light.
还有一个小时就要天黑了  我们还有很多地方要巡视
Today is history.
这是历史上的一天
■
——此段摘自阿蒙在1943年屠杀克拉科夫犹太人群体前，对士兵的“就职演讲”。
Today will be remembered.
今天将被永远纪念
Years from now, the young will ask with wonder about this day.
多年以后  年轻人将会对这一天充满憧憬
Today is history, and you are part of it.
今天我们将创造历史
Six hundred years ago...
六百年以前
...when elsewhere they were putting the blame for the Black Death...
他们在全世界其它各地因为黑死病而被唾弃
...Kazimiers The Great, so called...
但是卡斯米尔兹大帝
...told the Jews they could come to Krakow.
告诉犹太人  他们可以搬来克拉科夫
They came.
所以他们就来了
They trundled their belongings into the city.
他们将所有的家当都带来这里
They settled...
他们住了下来
...they took hold. They prospered...
落地生根  逐渐茁壮
...in business, science, education, the arts.
在商业、科学、教育及艺术方面取得了惊人的成就
They came here with nothing.
他们本来一无所有
Nothing!
两手空空
And they flourished.
然后他们在此开花结果
For six centuries there has been a Jewish Krakow.
六个世纪以来  克拉科夫一直被犹太人霸占着
Think about that.
你们想想看
By this evening...
但今晚之后
...those six centuries are a rumour.
这六个世纪将只是一个传说
They never happened.
从来没有存在过
Today is history!
我们今天即将改写历史
一九四三年三月十三日
犹太区屠杀清洗开始
■
事实上，入侵波兰后，战争的进程深入使得希特勒不再满
足于驱逐、分隔犹太人，而想实行“彻底”的种族灭绝，
于是，被称为“最后解决”的大屠杀开始了。除了党卫队
特别行动队自身外，还有募招当地警察和反犹的极端民族
主义分子，带头的还往往是些教员、医师或教士之流。他
们的残暴比德国人有过之而无不及，不得不说是波兰人的
悲哀，或者，是人类的悲哀。
Get off and line up in a two row!
全部下车站成两排
Come on, quicker!
动作快点
I think we will start, with Ghetto B.
我们从犹太B区开始
- All right?       - Start from both sides?
- 明白了吗？ - 从两边一起开始？
- No, no! I would like you to start there.       - The right side?
- 不  我要你从那边开始    - 先从右边
- And then move around.       - All right!
- 再掉头回来    - 好的
Label them clearly. They will follow you later on.
清楚地贴上标签  行李随后就会运到
Leave your luggage!
留下你的行李
Label them clearly.
清楚地贴上标签
They'll follow you later on.
行李随后就会运到
Open up!
开门
Come down!
下来
Jews, all out!
犹太人都出来
Put on something warm and come out.
穿上暖和的衣服  走出来
To Chodi Square!
到广场上来
Gold, Chaim! Go to Chodi Square.
汉恩•高德！快去广场
- Gold, Chaim!       - Yes, Chaim Gold.
- 汉恩•高德    - 我是汉恩•高德
Shoot him!
杀了他
Put on something warm and go to Chodi Square.
穿上暖和的衣服到广场上
No baggage! No baggage!
不要带行李
- Go through.       - No baggage! No baggage!
- 通过    - 不要带行李
Hey, little boy. How old are you, huh?
小宝贝  你叫什么名字？
Huh, what's your name? What's your name, huh?
你叫什么名字？你叫什么名字？
I said, no luggage!
我说了不要带行李
Don't pack, no luggage!
不能带行李
Go to Chodi Square! Leave your luggage here!
到广场上去  把你的行李放在这儿
- Blue card!       - Chodi Square!
- 蓝卡    - 去广场
What's this bag doing here?
带这个包要干什么？
Everybody to Chodi Square!
所有人都去广场
We're getting out through the sewers. I have to check if they're clear.
我们从下水道逃走  我先去看看安不安全
- Mila, pack some things. Nothing bigger...       - I can't go in the sewers.
- 蜜拉  赶快打包    - 我不要进下水道
I told you I won't go in the sewers.
我告诉过你我绝对不进下水道
You can go. Yes, you can.
你做得到的
I won't go in the sewers.
我不要
- Move!       - Over there! Over there! Move!
- 过去    - 动作快点  过去排队
Your card, Jew?
你的卡呢  犹太人？
Your papers, Jew?
你的识别卡呢  犹太人？
Your papers, Jew!
你的卡在哪里？
That line!
那条队伍
Your papers?
你的识别卡呢？
I'm not going up because of your goddamn papers!
因为你该死的识别卡 我不能上去
Your goddamn papers!
你那该死的识别卡
Why are you shooting? Are you crazy?
为什么开枪？你疯了？
In this traffic, you could have shot me!
在那种情况下  你差点打到我了
The bullet passed me by so close!
子弹离我这么近
- Sorry!       - Now you say sorry? You're crazy!
- 对不起    - 现在你说对不起了？你疯了！
Stay away! Stay away!
离远点  离远点
Don't talk, don't talk! Just go to the trucks!
不要说话  到卡车上去
Keep on walking, keep on walking! Don't talk!
继续走  不要说话
Come here, you fuckin' Jew!
到这来  该死的犹太人
Stand still! I said, stand still!
站着别动  我说站着别动
She's good as dead. Leave her.
她已经没救了  把她扔了
Give me a moment. Just let me bring her inside.
请给我几分钟  让我带她去医院
You can join her, or join the line.
你如果不想跟她陪葬  就快去排队
Women to the left!
女人靠左边
- Men to right.       - Women to the left!
- 男人靠右边     - 女人靠左边
- Women to the left.       - Let me go! I won't leave my husband!
- 女人靠左边    - 别拉我  我不要跟我先生分开
Women to the left, and men to the right.
女人靠左边  男人靠右边
Mama! Mama!
妈妈  妈妈
Mila!
蜜拉！
Oh, God, Danka!
天啊  丹卡
- You have a blue card.       - Blue card doesn't matter any more.
- 你有蓝卡    - 蓝卡现在不管用了
- They are cleaning out the ghetto.       - There's not enough room for you.
- 他们正在血洗犹太区    - 这里容不下你
What are you talking about? We tried it before. There's more than enough room.
你在说什么？我们试过的  绝对挤得下
- I changed my mind!       - Mama!
- 我改变主意了    - 妈妈
Look at the space in there. Now look at me. You are just scared.
你自己看看里面多宽敞  看着我  你只是害怕罢了
I can fit the girl, but not you.
我可以收容你女儿  但你得走
- Mama, I'm coming out!       - Stay where you are.
- 妈妈  我要跟你一起    - 你别出来
I'd rather you be here than who knows where.
我宁愿你安全待在这里
Mama!
妈妈
Commander!
指挥官大人
Very good saluting.
敬礼敬得很标准嘛
I respectfully report I've been given orders to clear the bundles from the road.
报告长官  我被指派来清空路面
So there will be no obstructions to the thoroughfare.
好让军队能顺利通行
Finish and join the lines, little Polish clicking soldier.
赶快清  清完了就去排队  这个人真逗
Mrs. Dresner?
你是椎斯纳太太？
Yes.
是的
Oh, you are a friend of my son's.
你是我儿子的朋友
Don't worry, I'll go quietly. I'll be no trouble.
别担心  我静静地走  不会给你惹麻烦的
No, get under the stairs. They'll be done searching soon. You'll be safe there.
不  你藏在楼梯底下  他们快要检查完了  你在这里很安全
Please hide! Please!
赶快躲起来
Hide under the stairs!
躲到楼梯下去
I've searched the building. There's no one here.
这栋大楼我已经检查过了  里面没有人
- Okay, then we're going to the next block.       - Understood!
- 很好 我们去下一个街区    - 明白
- Danka!       - Mama!
- 丹卡   - 妈妈
Hello, Adam.
你好  亚当
Hello, Danka.
你好  丹卡
Come with me. I will put you in the good line.
跟我来  我会把你们放到好的队伍里
Do you know the saying, "An hour of life is still life"?
你没听说过吗？"片刻的生命也是生命"
You are not a boy any more. I'm saying a blessing for you.
你已经不是小孩了  我会为你祷告的
■
在山头上骑马驻足的辛德勒静静的看着下面异常混乱的街道，在黑白颜色的
人群中，一个衣着红色的小女孩儿在其中快速的毫无目的穿梭着。值得一提
的是，全片只有两种色调，黑与白，所以，这个红衣小女孩儿显得特别的醒
目。在由童声合唱组成的低沉背景音乐中，小女孩儿身上的红色代表着生命，
尽管它看上去是那么的脆弱。
Oh, please, let's go. Let's go, please!
求求你  我们走吧  不要看了
Come on!
走吧
Mark it...
标记这里
...mark it!
- What is it? Is it Bach?       - No, no. It's Mozart.
- 那是谁的作品  是巴哈吗？ - 不  是莫扎特
- Mozart?       - Yes!
- 是莫扎特？ - 对
I wish this fucking night were over.
真希望今晚赶快结束
Caps off!
脱掉帽子
Sort the names!
开始点名
Those who're announced will raise their hands and shout a clear "Yes"!
叫到名字的  要举手示意并大声喊到
Yes!
到
Disband!
解散
The worst is over. We are workers now.
最糟的已经过去了  我们现在是工人
Oh, God, Amon!
天啊  阿蒙
Go to your barracks immediately!
立刻回到自己的营房
Amon, you're such a damned fuckin' child!
阿蒙  你这个幼稚的混蛋
Wakey, wakey.
快起床吧
- Make coffee.       - Make it yourself.
- 去煮点咖啡    - 你自己去煮
The SS will manage certain industries itself inside Plaszow.
在普拉邵  纳粹亲卫队会自己管理一些工厂
A metalworks, brush factory...
其中包括一间金属工厂  一间刷子工厂
...another for reprocessing jewish clothing from the ghettos...
另外一个厂房是专门收集整理从犹太区搜刮来的衣物
...for use by bombed-out families back home.
用来接济在德国被轰炸的家庭
But it's private industry like yours that stands to benefit most...
但是像你这样的私人公司  如果能搬到劳动营里
...by moving inside the wire of Commandant Amon Goeth's camp...
可以获得最大的效益…
No, no, no. Sit, sit. Julian, how are you?
别起来  胡利安  你好吗？
Good to see you, my friend.
真高兴见到你  我的朋友
- Oskar Schindler.       - Leo John.
- 奥斯卡•辛德勒    - 我是李欧•约翰
- Franz, good to see you.       - Hello, Oskar. Glad you could join us.
- 方斯  好久不见    - 你好  很高兴你能加入
- My pleasure. Julius.       - How are you? You lost weight.
- 那是我的荣幸  胡利斯    - 你好吗？你好像瘦了
Only in the shoulders. Please, everybody, sit down.
只是肩膀瘦了而已  大家请坐啊
How are you doing? Oskar Schindler.
你好  我是奥斯卡•辛德勒
- We started without you.       - Fine. I miss anything good?
- 我们先开动了    - 没关系  我错过了什么吗？
I was explaining to Herr Bosch and Herr Madritsch...
我正在跟博司先生和麦翠屈先生解释…
...some of the benefits of moving their factories into Plaszow.
把他们的工厂移入普拉邵的好处
I meant the food.
我是说吃的
Since your labour is housed on-site, it's available to you at all times.
因为你的工人都会被集中关在这儿  所以随时都可以开工
You can work them all night if you want.
你甚至可以要求他们24小时不停工作
Your factory policies, whatever they've been in the past, they'll continue to be.
你工厂过去的规定  不论以前是怎么样  现在一样照旧
They'll be respected.
我们尊重你们的规定
I have to know, where do you get a suit like that? What is that? Is that silk?
我很想知道你的西装是在哪买的？是丝绸做的吗？
Of course!
当然
Yeah, it's, it has a nice sheen about it.
看起来非常有光泽
- Thank you.       - Very nice.
- 谢谢    - 非常漂亮
I'd say I'd get you one, but the man who made it is probably dead.
平常我会说我送你一套  不过这个裁缝师可能已经死了
I don't know.
我也不确定
I go to work the other day.
我前几天去我工厂上班时
Nobody's there.
发现里面空无一人
Nobody tells me about this. I have to find out. I have to go in.
甚至没有人事先知会我一声  我得自己去了才知道
Everybody's gone.
大家都不见了
No!
不
不是的
They're not gone. They're here.
他们不是不见了  他们都在这里
They're mine! Every day that goes by, I'm losing money.
可他们是我的工人  我每天都在损失金钱
Every worker that is shot costs me money. I have to find somebody else.
每死一个工人我就损失一点钱  我得再去请人
I have to trade them!
重新训练
We are going to be making so much money that none of this is going to matter.
我们以后会赚很多很多钱  到时候这些都不算什么
It's bad business.
生意不是这样做的
Thank you.
谢谢你
Leave the bottle.
整瓶留下就好了
Take that.
把这拿走
Lena, thank you.
海伦  谢谢你
Scherner told me something else about you.
尚纳告诉过我你的事情
Yeah? What's that?
是吗？像是什么事？
That you know the meaning of the word "gratitude. "
他说你是个"知恩图报"的人
That it's not some vague thing with you...
而且你不像其他人只是嘴上说说
...like it is with others.
你是真的很大方
You want to stay where you are.
你不想把工厂迁进来
You've got things going on the side.
因为你平常也搞其他的副业
Things are good.
而且做得有声有色
You don't want anybody telling you what to do.
你不想别人坏了你的大事
I can understand all that, you know? I know you.
这些我都能了解  我了解你这种人
What you want... is your own sub-camp.
你想要的是你自己的小型劳动营
Do you have any idea what is involved? The paperwork alone?
你知道那有多麻烦吗？光是文件就可以整死你
You've got to build the fucking thing. Getting the fucking permits is enough to drive you crazy.
你得先建一个营房  光是申请许可证就足以使人发疯
Then the engineers show up, they stand around, they argue about drainage, foundations...
然后工程师就会跑来跟你吵一堆排水、地基的奇怪问题
...codes, exact specifications, fences 4 kilometres long, 1,200 kilograms of barbed wire...
什么围栏一定要四公里长  还要一千两百公斤的刺网
...6,000 kilograms of electrified fences, ceramic insulators...
六千公斤的电网、陶瓷绝缘体
...three cubic metres of air space per prisoner.
每个犯人还需要三立方的空间
I'm telling you, you want to shoot somebody. I've been through it. I know.
我告诉你  你真的会很想枪毙几个人  这是我的亲身经历
Well, you know. You've been through it.
当然啦  我相信你真的经历过
You could make things easier for me.
你可以特别通融我
I'd be grateful.
我会很感激的
Where's Stern?
史登在哪里？
Goldberg and Chilowicz, make sure I see my cut...
古柏特和施洛维兹负责监督营内其他的工厂
...from the, uh, factory owners in this camp...
确保那些人不会亏待我
...leaving you to take care of my main account...
你一个人全权负责我的大金主
...the Schindler account.
辛德勒的帐户
He wants his independence. I gave it to him.
他想要独立自由  我成全了他
But independence costs money.
但是自由的代价是昂贵的
This you understand?
这你了解吗？
Look at me!
看着我
Don't forget who you are working for now.
不要忘了你现在是替谁工作
Make sure he stays. He's a slippery bastard!
要保证让他留下来  他是个狡猾的家伙
- We need more wine.       - More wine!
- 我们需要更多的酒    - 更多的酒！
Stand on my friend. Don't let him leave.
站在他的脚上  不要让他离开
Thank you, Mr. Director.
谢谢您  厂长先生
Cheers, Mr. Director!
干杯  厂长先生
- What are you doing?       - What? Scratching my head.
- 你在干嘛啊？ - 什么？搔我的头吗？
Makes them think we have lice. Helps make them keep their distance.
我要让他们以为我们有头虱  这样他们会离我们远一点
- Do you have lice?       - Do you have your notebook?
- 你有头虱吗？  - 笔记本带了没？
The calendar on my desk has the birthdays of our SS friends' wives and children.
我桌上的日历中记着跟我们友好的每个纳粹高官家属的生日
Don't forget to send something.
别忘了送礼
Record pay-offs to the Main Administration and Economics Office, the Armaments...
我把给主计部、经济部和…
- Slowly, Stern, slowly.       - The Armaments Board...
- 慢一点  史登  慢一点   - 军备部...
...Governor General's Division of the Interior and Chief of Police as "fees"...
内政部和警察总长的贿款登记在"支出"底下
...and make them on the first of each month...
每个月的第一天就要寄出
...as opposed to individual pay-offs to our SS contacts.
至于我们单独收买的纳粹亲卫队员
The list is in the lower drawer of my desk...
那个清单在我桌子下面的抽屉…
"First of month... "
"每个月的第一天"
SS contacts: List, lower drawer of my desk, which you handle...
纳粹亲卫队员收买清单在下面的抽屉  付款方法是…
...as cash contributions to legitimate charities sent to each official's office.
以慈善基金的名义  用现金直接送去他们个人的办公室
Dealings with our black market contacts, listed as suppliers...
至于我们黑市的接头人
-... in the legitimate ledger, are more complicated.       - Forget it!
- 是登记在合法的供应商底下…    - 算了
- What do you mean, you can't forget it!       - It gives me a headache!
- 怎么能算了？你不能这样就放弃    - 我的头快要炸开了
- I couldn't get you out of here.       - I'll be all right.
- 我无法把你救出来    - 我在这里没事
Anyway, I'm here almost every week. Wednesdays, usually.
我每个星期都会到这里来  通常是星期三
I'll look in on you, see how you're doing.
我会来看看你过得如何
Here, put these in your pocket.
这个  放到你的口袋里去
Come on!
快点
Mr. Director, don't let things fall apart. I've worked too hard.
不要放弃我们的帐户  我花了很大功夫才经营起来的
Thanks for... Good luck!
多谢…  祝你好运
Attention! Caps off!
立正！脱掉帽子！
- Work!       - Back to work!
- 工作    - 回去工作吧
普拉邵强制劳动营内的金属加工厂
- What are you making?       - Hinges, sir!
- 你在做些什么？ - 长官  我负责制造铰链
Yeah, I've got some workers coming in tomorrow. Where are they from again?
明天会有一批新的工人被送来  他们是打哪来的？
Yugoslavia, Mr. Commander!
是南斯拉夫  指挥官大人
I've got to make room.
这里太挤了  我得清掉一些人
- Make me a hinge.       - Yes, sir!
- 做一个铰链给我    - 是的  长官
Keep going, you're doing well.
做得很不错嘛
Says he's doing well.
说他做得很不错
Oh, that's very good.
真的很不错
But I'm a bit confused, and perhaps you can help me.
但是我有一点不明白  或许你能替我解答
What I don't understand is that you've been working...
我想不通的是  你今天从…
.. since I think, what, about 6.00 this morning?
我想大概是六点就开始工作了吧
Yet such a small pile of hinges.
怎么只做了那么一点点铰链
- Oh, Christ.       - May I try that, sir?
- 该死的    - 长官  请容我试试
Check the angle lever. Maybe it's bent.
检查看看杠杆  或许那里弯了
No, no. You wouldn't hear a click if it was the angle lever.
不可能  要是杠杆弯了  枪枝根本不会发出声音
Maybe the pin shaft is greasy.
一定是调弦栓被油污卡住了
What did I just say? Here.
我就说吧  好了
Mr. Commander!
指挥官大人
I beg to report that my heap of hinges was so unsatisfactory...
请容许我报告一下  我的工作台上之所以只有几个铰链
...because the machines were being recalibrated this morning.
是因为今天早上机器被查校调整过
I was put on to shoveling coal.
那时我被指派去铲煤
Strange, huh?
很奇怪吧？
Thank you, Muek.
谢谢你  慕克
Ah, Lisiek. Don't touch the leather, it's just been oiled.
李谢克  别碰到皮面  我刚刚才上过油
- Squad leader!       - Oh, for me?
- 下士     - 给我的吗？
- Oh, thank you very much, Mr Director.       - Mr. Director!
- 太感谢您了  厂长先生    - 厂长先生
Mr. Director!
厂长先生
He was making hinges slowly.
因为他桌上只有一小堆铰链
So the man can turn out a hinge in less than a minute. Why the long story?
所以你说的是其实他做铰链做得很快  难道不能长话短说吗？
李瓦图
- Thank you, sir.       - You're welcome!
- 感谢您  先生    - 不客气
Nobody knows who stole the chicken?       - Tell him about the chicken.
- 没有人知道鸡是谁偷的？ - 赶快从实招来
A man walks around with a chicken and nobody notices this.
一个人手提着一只鸡走来走去  竟然会没有人注意到
Save yourselves.
救救你们自己吧
Tell him about the chicken.
赶快从实招来
Still nobody knows?
还是没有人知道
It was you! You committed this crime!
就是你  鸡是你偷的
- No, sir.       - But you know who, though.
- 不是的  长官    - 但是你知道是谁
- Yes.       - Who?
- 是的    - 是谁？
Him!
就是他！
- He's very gifted.       - Yeah, sure. Bring him over.
- 他是个天才儿童    - 好吧  让他来我那儿上班
Sir, thank you.
谢谢先生
- Thank you again, Mr. Director!       - You're welcome again.
- 再次感谢您  厂长先生    - 不用这么客气
It's an honour to work for such a great company.
能为这么伟大的工厂做事  是我的荣幸
It's great to have you!
我也很高兴有你这么好的员工
I promise to learn everything there's to know about enamelware production.
我将会竭尽所能去学习制作搪瓷器皿的一切知识
That's great!
很好
- Hello? Miss Elsa Krause is here.       - I only need five minutes.
- 有一位艾莎•克劳斯小姐求见    - 我只需要五分钟
She wants to speak to Mr. Director.
她想要见厂长先生
Yes.
好的
He won't see you.
他不愿意见你
Please, sit down.
请坐
- Pernod? Cognac?       - Uh, no. No, thank you.
- 要来点白兰地吗？ - 不用了  谢谢您
So, what can I do for you?
有什么我能效劳的？
They say that no one dies here.
大家都说在这里没有人会被枪毙
They say your factory is a haven.
大家都说您这里是个安全的避难所
They say you are good.
大家都说您是个大好人
Who says that?
那是谁说的？
Everyone.
大家都这么说
My name is Regina Perlman, not Elsa Krause.
我的真名是蕾金娜•帕尔曼  不是艾莎•克劳斯
I've been living in Krakow on false papers since the ghetto massacre.
在犹太区的大屠杀之后  我一直用假证件住在克拉科夫
My parents are in Plaszow.
可是我的父母被关在普拉邵
Their names are Chana and Jakob Perlman.
他们的名字是汉娜和雅各•帕尔曼
They are older people. They are killing older people now in Plaszow.
他们年纪都很老了  纳粹现在在屠杀普拉邵里的老人
They bury them up in the forest. Look...
还把他们埋在森林里  是这样的
...I don't have any money.
我身无分文
I, I borrowed these clothes.
这些衣服也是借来的
I'm begging you.
我求你了
Please, please bring them here.
求你把他们接过来
I don't do that.
我从来不做这种事
You've been misled. I ask one thing:
是你搞错了  我只雇用能替我干活的人
Whether or not a worker has certain skills.
我只在乎他们有没有专业技能
My father is an importer, not a metalworker.
我父亲是个进口商  不是个金属工人
Such activities are illegal. You will not entrap me!
你的要求是违法的  你休想陷害我  克劳斯小姐！
Cry, and I will have you arrested. I swear to God!
我发誓你若是敢掉一滴眼泪  我就把你送去警察局
People die. It's a fact of life.
人都会死  这是人生不变的定律
He wants to kill everybody? Great! What am I supposed to do about it?
他要是想把每个人都杀掉  我又能拿他怎么办？
Bring everybody over? Is that what you think?
难不成把大家都接来？这是你的如意算盘吗？
Send them over to Schindler. Send them all!
把他们送到辛德勒那里去  把他们全送去
His place is a haven, didn't you know? It's not a factory.
他那里是个避难所  你没有听说过吗？那里不是个工厂
It's not an enterprise of any kind.
也不是个正经工作赚钱的地方
It's a haven for rabbis and orphans...
那里是牧师和孤儿的收容所
...and people with no skills whatsoever!
完全不需要任何专业技能
You think I don't know what you're doing?
你以为我不知道你在搞什么鬼？
You're so quiet all the time. I know, I know!
你总是那么的安静  其实我心知肚明
- Are you losing money?       - That's not the point!
- 难道我没有替你赚大钱？ - 那个不是重点
- What other point is...       - It's dangerous! It's dangerous to me!
- 重点是...    - 那样做太危险了  可能危害到我的安全
You have to understand. Goeth is under enormous pressure.
你必须了解  葛斯他身上承担了很大的压力
You have to think of it in his situation.
你必须设身处地的替他想想
He's got this whole place to run.
他必须管理这么大的地方
He's responsible for everything here, all these people.
他必须为所有的人和事物负责
He's got a lot of things to worry about.
他的烦恼可不轻
And he's got the war which brings out the worst in people.
而且战争往往把人性中最黑暗的一面引出来
Never the good, always the bad. Always the bad.
战争总是带出人的黑暗面  从来不会激发光明面
But in normal circumstances he wouldn't be like this. He'd be all right.
要是换作平时  他绝对不是这样的人  他会是个不错的人
There'd just be the good aspects of him which...
他也有他好的一面…
He's a wonderful crook.
他不过是个小恶霸
A man who loves good food, good wine, the ladies, making money...
他喜欢美食、醇酒、美女和白花花的银子…
Killing!
他喜欢杀人
He can't enjoy it.
没有人天生就喜欢杀人
Bejski told me the other day, somebody escaped...
贝耶斯基前几天告诉我
...from a work detail outside the wire.
有人在工作的时候逃跑了
Goeth lined up everybody from the missing man's barracks.
葛斯叫那整个营房的人排排站好
He shot the man to the left of Bejski, the man to the right of him.
他枪毙了站在贝耶斯基左边和右边的人
He walked down the line shooting every other man with a pistol.
他一边走一边用自己的手枪跳着枪毙每排的人
Twenty-five!
死了二十五人
- What do you want me to do about it?       - Nothing, nothing.
- 那你希望我怎么办？ - 不怎么办
We're just talking.
我们只是随便聊聊
"Perlman. "
帕尔曼
Perlman!
Husband and wife.
那是一对老夫妇
Jakob and Chana Perlman!
雅各和汉娜•帕尔曼
Have Goldberg bring them over.
叫古柏特把他们带到工厂来
德国搪瓷厂
I'm sure this will be better than those rags, Lisiek.
这个应该会比抹布有用  李谢克
Mr. Director, I was just helping Lisiek to find something...
厂长先生  我只是在帮李谢克找东西
...to clean the stains from the Commander's bathtub.
好清洁指挥官大人浴缸里的污渍
- Go clean it.       - Pardon me, Sir!
- 快去吧    - 很抱歉  厂长先生
You don't have to report to me, Helen.
海伦  你不用向我报告
You know who I am?
你知道我是谁吗？
I'm Schindler.
我是辛德勒
Of course. I, I have heard and...
是的  我有听说过
...you have been here before.
而且您以前也来过这里作客
Here, why don't you keep this someplace?
拿去  把这个收起来
- Go on, take it.       - I get extra food here.
- 拿去啊  没关系的    - 我这里有足够的食物
Well, if you don't want to eat it, trade it. Or give it to Lisiek.
如果你不喜欢  也可以拿去跟别人交换  或着送给李谢克
Why not build yourself up?
你这么瘦弱  该多吃一点了
My first day here, he beat me...
我第一天来这的时候  他就毒打了我一顿
...because I threw out the bones from dinner.
只因为我把晚餐剩的骨头扔了
He came down to the basement at midnight, and he...
他半夜的时候  跑进地下室来
...he asked me where they were.
他问我骨头到哪去了
For his dogs, you understand?
因为他想拿骨头给他的狗吃
I said to him, I, I don't know how I say this.
我反问他…  我当时真不知道是吃错什么药了
I never could say it now, I said to him...
我竟然问他
..."Why are you beating me?"
"你为什么要这样打我？"
He said, "The reason I beat you now...
他回答"我之所以打你"
...is because you ask why I beat you. "
"是因为你胆敢问我这种问题"
I know your sufferings, Helen.
我了解你所受的苦  海伦
It doesn't matter.
这些都不重要
I have accepted them.
我已经接纳了我的命运
Accepted them?
你接纳了什么？
One day he will shoot me.
有一天  他会一枪杀了我
No, no, no, no, he won't shoot you.
不  他绝对不会杀了你
I know. I see things.
是真的  是我亲眼看到的
We were on the roof on Monday, young Lisiek and I...
星期一的时候  我跟李谢克站在阳台上
and we saw the Commander come out of the front door and...
我们看到指挥官大人从前门走了出来
...and down the steps by the patio right there below us and...
就在我们的正下方  离前院阶梯不远的地方
...and there on the steps he drew his gun and he...
他站在那里  把枪拔了出来
...shot a woman who was passing by.
然后他一枪打死了一个路过的女人
A woman carrying a bundle. Through the throat.
那个女人手里拿着一个包裹  被一枪射穿了喉咙
Just-Just a woman on her way somewhere, you know.
只是一个刚好路过的女人
She was no fatter or thinner...
她跟其他的人根本没有什么不同
...or slower or faster than anyone else...
外貌和举止并没有特别之处
...and I couldn't guess what had she done.
我无法想象她到底是招谁惹谁了
The more you see of the Commander...
越是近距离的观察指挥官大人
...the more you see there is no set rules that you can live by.
我就越觉得命在旦夕  无所适从
You can't say to yourself, "If I follow these rules, I will be safe. "
我根本无法预料他的喜怒哀乐和行事准则
He won't shoot you because he enjoys you too much.
他太喜欢你了  他绝对不会伤害你的
He enjoys you so much he won't even let you wear the star.
他甚至不要你穿戴犹太人的臂章
He doesn't want anyone else to know, it's a Jew he's enjoying.
他不希望别人知道  他喜欢的是一个犹太女孩
He shot the woman from the steps because she meant nothing to him.
他之所以杀了那个台阶旁的女人  是因为她对他来说毫无意义
She was one of a series neither offending or pleasing him.
她不过是其中一个犹太囚犯  既不讨他喜欢  也不惹他讨厌
But you, Helen!
但是你就不同了  海伦
It's all right. It's not that kind of a kiss.
别紧张  我并无意冒犯你
Thank you!
谢谢你
Here!
拿着
Right, the wine!
对了  我的酒
Wonderful party, Amon. Thank you.
很成功的舞会  阿蒙  谢谢你
Why do you drink that motor oil?
你怎么老是喝那种劣酒？
I send you good stuff all the time.
枉费我一天到晚送好酒给你
Your liver's going to explode like a hand grenade.
总有一天你的肝脏会像手榴弹一样爆掉
You know, I look at you...
知道吗  我总是看着你…
...I watch you!
我在观察你
You're never drunk.
你从来都不会喝醉
Oh, that's...
那是…
...that's real control.
那就是绝佳的自制力
Control is power.
自制力就是权力
That's power.
你拥有权力
Is that why they fear us?
那是他们惧怕我们的原因？
We have the fucking power to kill, that's why they fear us.
他们惧怕我们是因为我们掌控了他们的生杀大权
They fear us because we have the power to kill arbitrarily.
他们惧怕我们是因为我们毫无节制的乱杀人
A man commits a crime, he should know better.
如果一个人是因为犯了重罪遭到惩罚  那是他罪有应得
We have him killed, and we feel pretty good about it.
如果我们让他被处死  那是一件令人开心的事
Or we kill him ourselves and we feel even better.
又如果我们自己亲手杀了他  那更是大快人心
That's not power, though.
但是那并不是权力
That's justice. It's different than power.
那是制裁  跟权力完全是两回事
Power is when we have every justification to kill...
所谓的权力是当我们有绝对的理由去杀生
...and we don't.
但我们却不这么做
You think that's power?
你认为那才是权力？
That's what the emperors had. A man stole something...
这是古代帝王的风范  一个人犯了偷窃罪
...he's brought in before the emperor...
他被带到帝王的面前
...he throws himself down on the ground, he begs for mercy.
他扑倒在地  恳求帝王饶他一命
He knows he's going to die.
他知道他的小命不保
And the emperor, pardons him.
结果帝王饶恕了他
This worthless man. He lets him go.
他饶恕了一个微不足道的人
I think you are drunk.
我看你是醉了
That's power, Amon.
那才是权力  阿蒙
That, is power!
那才是权力
Amon the good!
阿蒙  慈爱者
I pardon you!
我饶恕你
What do they want?
他们想要干嘛？
I don't know, but they're in my office right now reviewing our books.
我也不知道  但是他们现在在我的办公室里翻阅帐册
As my accountant, tell me, should I be alarmed...
你身为我的会计  告诉我…
...that the auditors are reviewing my books?
我应该要担心国税局的人在查阅我的帐册吗？
- Or have you done your job properly?       - You needn't be alarmed.
- 还是你有把一切处理得天衣无缝    - 您一点也不需要担心
I needn't be alarmed!
我一点也不需要担心
- I'm sorry, sir.       - Do you know how much this saddle is worth?
- 很抱歉  大人    - 你知道这个马鞍值多少钱吗？
Do you know how much it costs?
你知道这花了我多少银子？
All right!
算了
Stern, what the hell are you doing following me around?
你干嘛还一直跟着我？
She was smoking on the job.
她在工作时抽烟
Tell her not to do it again.
叫她以后别再犯了
I have to report, sir...
我得向您报告  大人…
...I've been unable to remove the stains from your bathtub.
我没有办法去除掉浴缸上的污渍
- What are you using, Lisiek?       - Soap, Commander.
- 你是用什么清洁浴缸的  李谢克？ - 报告长官  用的是肥皂
Soap? Not lye?
肥皂？怎么不用卤水？
Go ahead, go on, leave. Leave, I pardon you.
算了  你走吧  我饶恕你
I pardon you!
我饶恕你
Although I am not a rabbi, in these circumstances...
因为我们现在身处非常时期  所以我虽然不是牧师
...I pray to the Almighty that he will forgive me...
仍祈求神能够原谅我
...if I intone the blessings.
让我主持今天的婚礼
So...
原来…
...this is where you come to hide from me.
你平常就是自己一个人躲在这里
I came to tell you...
我是来告诉你
...that you, um, you really are a wonderful cook and a well-trained servant.
你是一个很棒的厨子  也是一个训练有素的女佣
I mean it. If you need a reference after the war...
我是说真的  如果你在战后需要有人给你写推荐信
...I'd be, I'd be happy to give you one.
我会非常乐意效劳
It must get lonely down here when you're..
你总是一个人在这里聆听
...listening to everyone upstairs having such a good time.
楼上人们欢乐的声音  一定觉得份外寂寞
Does it?
不是吗？
You can answer.
你可以回答
But what's the right answer? That's what you're thinking:
但是怎么回答才正确？你一定是在这么想
"What does he want to hear?"
"他到底想听些什么？"
The truth, Helen, is always the right answer.
海伦  实话永远是正确的答案
Yes, you're right.
是的  你说得没错
Sometimes we're both lonely.
有时我们都很孤独
Yes. I...
是的  我…
...I mean...
我是说…
...I would like so much to...
我好希望能够…
...reach out and touch you in your loneliness.
向你伸出双手  去触碰你的寂寞
Wh- what would that be like, I wonder? I mean...
不知那会是什么样的感觉  我是说…
...what would be wrong with that?
难道那样是错的吗？
I realize that you're not a-a person in the...
我知道  严格的说起来
...the strictest sense of the word, but...
你并不能算是个人  但是…
No, maybe you're right about that too, you know, maybe what's...
不  也许你才是对的
...what's wrong isn't...
这其中错误的…
...it's not us!
并不是我们
It's, no, it's this!
错的是这个世界
I mean, when they compare you to...
我是说  当他们把你…
...to, uh, vermin and to rodents and to lice...
跟社会的败类、害虫和鼠辈相提并论时
...I just, uh...
我实在是…
No, no, you, you make a good point.
不  你说得很有道理
You make a very good point.
你说得非常有道理
Is this the face of a rat?
难道这是一张鼠辈的脸？
Are these the eyes of a rat?
而这双是老鼠的眼睛？
Hath not a Jew eyes?
难道犹太人不该有眼睛吗？
I feel for you, Helen.
我很喜欢你  海伦
No, I don't think so.
不  你休想这样轻易迷惑我
You're a Jewish bitch!
你这只犹太母狗
You nearly talked me into it, didn't you?
你差点说服了我  是不是？
Bravo!
太棒了
- Bravo!       - Cheers! Cheers!
- 太棒了    - 干杯  干杯
On behalf of the, of the workers, sir, I, I wish for you a happy birthday.
谨代表所有的员工  祝您生日快乐
Happy birthday!
生日快乐
Well, the staff, please.
请替我谢谢大家
Thank you very much for the lovely cake.
也谢谢你们送给我这么棒的蛋糕
Thank you very much. Tell them "Thank you" from me.
非常感谢  请代我向大家致意
The trains arrived and the people were driven out with clubs.
火车到站之后  大家就被士兵拿着棍子赶下车来
They were lined up in front of two big warehouses.
士兵要大家在两个大仓库前排成一行
One was marked "Cloak Room" and the other "Valuables. "
其中一间上面写着"大衣间"  另外一间写着"贵重物品"
And there they were made to undress.
他们被强迫把衣服都脱了
A Jewish boy handed them pieces of string to tie their shoes together.
一个犹太小男孩递给大家绳子  好把鞋子都绑起来
They shaved their hair.
他们的头发也都被剃光
They told them it was needed to make something special for U-boat crews.
士兵说那是潜艇队员的发型
And then they were herded down a big corridor...
然后他们被赶进一条回廊
...to bunkers with Stars of David on the doors...
从那里他们来到一个上面画有大卫之星的燃料仓
...and signs that said "Bath and Inhalation Room"
还有一块牌子写着"淋浴和蒸气室"
SS gave them soap.
纳粹亲卫队还给了大家肥皂
They told them to breathe all the time because it's good for disinfecting.
他们特意吩咐大家要大力呼吸  因为蒸气可以消毒杀菌
And then they gassed them.
就这样  大家都被毒气毒死了
Mila, why soaps?
蜜拉  为什么要给大家肥皂？
So that they would agree to go in, I think.
大概是因为这样听起来比较有说服力吧
Come on, Mila, stop it. Your bedtime stories are scaring everyone.
蜜拉  别说了  你的睡前故事快把大家都吓死了
- I just don't believe it.       -Ja. You know it's ridiculous.
- 我才不相信呢    - 是啊  这个故事太荒唐了
- I don't believe it either.       - I cannot believe it.
- 我也不相信    - 我不相信
- I didn't say I believed it. I said I heard it.       - From who?
- 我没说我相信  我只是转述而已    - 你听谁说的？
From somebody who heard it from someone who was there.
一个在集中营里的人
You know, if they were there, they would have been gassed.
如果他们在场也会被毒死啊
- Yes!       - It doesn't make any sense.
- 是啊    - 这样根本说不通
We're their workforce.
我们是德军的劳动力
What sense does it make to kill your own workforce?
把劳动力杀光这种做法怎么说得通？
To go to all this trouble of assembling a workforce only to...
大费周章组成劳动营就为了…
No, it can't be true.
这不是真的
We are very, very important for them.
我们对他们非常非常重要
Yes, we do now! Goodnight.
至少现在是  晚安
- Goodnight.       - Goodnight. Sweet dreams.
- 晚安   - 晚安  祝你好梦
Attention, attention!
请注意！请注意！
Everyone who is alive...
凡是活着的人...
...is to come to the roll-call area!
都请立刻到操场集合
- Attention, attention!       - We have to go to the roll-call area!
- 请注意！请注意！  - 我们必须到操场去
- Everyone who is alive... The list makers are here.
- 凡是活着的人...    - 造名册的人来了
- ... is to come to the roll-call area.       - There is going to be a selection.
- 都请立刻到操场集合    - 他们要进行筛选
Attention, attention. Everyone who is alive...
请注意  请注意！凡是活着的人...
...is to come to the roll-call area!
都请立刻到操场集合
100.000 Hungarian is coming.
十万个匈牙利人就要来了
You could afford to lose some weight, Amon.
你不妨减轻一点体重
And you've got to cut down on the cognac.
而且要少喝白兰地
Morning. What's going on?
早安  怎么回事？
It's another semi-annual physical.
又是半年一次的体检
- There!       - I've got another shipment coming in of...
- 那边    - 我有一批新的货要来
What are they this time?
这次是什么人？
- Hungarians.       - Oh, yeah, Hungarians!
- 匈牙利人    - 匈牙利人
We've got to separate the sick from the healthy to make room.
必须淘汰那些病号  空出一点地方
Look alive, Rebeka.
打起精神来  蕾贝卡
That's my mechanic.
那是我的修车工人
Whose bright idea was it to get rid of him?
是谁自作聪明要把他弄走？
No, no, no! Wait, go away. She can work.
不对  不对  等一下  走开  她能做工
Come here. Look, separate the sick from the healthy.
听着  把健康的和病号分开
Those who can work and those who can't. She can work.
能做工和不能做工的分开  她能做工
You can work, you can come.
你能做工  过来
On your feet! On your feet!
站住  站住
Those not selected for transport, put your clothes back on.
通过体检没被刷掉的人  把衣服穿上
- Go back to the barracks.       - Return to the barracks.
- 请回营房去    - 请回营房去
Go back to the barracks!
回营房去
Oh, my God!
我的天！
- Olek? Olek?       - Danka?
- 欧力克呢？ - 丹卡
Olek? Olek?
欧力克呢？
Olek! Olek!
欧力克
- Olek?       - Danka?
- 欧力克？ - 丹卡？
- Danka?       - Olek?
- 丹卡？ - 欧力克？
Back to the barracks! Go back to your barracks!
请回营房去  请回到自己的营房去
- I didn't see him!       - They're hiding. I'm telling you, they're hiding.
- 我没看到他    - 他们躲起来了  我知道
I know Danka. She knows a good place. She took all of them together.
我了解丹卡  她带他们去躲了起来
Back to the barracks!
请回营房去
Find your own hiding place. There's no room for you here. Go away, quick!
自己找地方躲  这里挤不下了  快走开！
■
小男孩奥利趁乱逃出，四处找寻但找不到可以藏身的地方，只好钻进厕所的
粪坑里，就是在这个极其肮脏的地方，还躲着四五个小孩。孩子们稚嫩的脸
上沾满了污秽的粪水，奥利望着头上的蓝天，那肮脏的空气中还在回响着慈
母般的音乐……
Get out. This is our place. Get out!
出去  这是我们的地方  出去
- Oskar!       - Amon! Gentlemen!
- 奥斯卡    - 阿蒙  各位
- Why didn't you call me?       - I tried to call you. Here, Hujar, move.
- 怎么不打电话通知我？ - 我有打  胡加  让座
- Quite a picnic, huh? Madritsch!       - Oskar!
- 真丰盛的野餐  麦翠屈    - 奥斯卡
They're running a little late. It's taking longer than I thought.
就快好了  事情比我想象中更花时间
- A drink?       - Something cold. Bowle.
- 来一杯？  - 来杯冰的吧
Oh, another beautiful day.
又是美好的一天
The loading of the transport wagons is finished.
运输车已装载完毕
We can start!
可以出发了
Water! Water!
水 水
Water, water!
Oh, thank you.
谢谢
What do you say we get your fire hoses out here and hose down the cars? Thank you.
我们拿你的消防水管来洗车如何？谢谢
Indulge me!
好玩嘛
- Hujar!       - Yes, sir!
- 胡加      - 是
- Go bring the fire hoses.       - Where's the fire?
- 拿消防水管来    - 哪里失火了？
In the windows. That's it, that's it.
往车窗里喷  对
On the roof. That's it, good, good. In the window, in the window.
还有车顶  好  往车窗里
Come on. Come on.
喷啊  喷啊
That's it, more, more!
别停  再多喷一点
That's it, that's it. More, more!
很好  再来
This is really cruel, Oskar. You are giving them hope.
你太残忍了  奥斯卡  你在给他们希望
You shouldn't do that. That's cruel!
你这样不对吧  真残忍
Come on, try and reach the far end. Look out!
快点  尽量往后面喷  小心
- Water!    - More water!
- 水   - 更多的水
I've got some 200 metre hoses back in Emalia.
我在工厂里还有条两百公尺长的水管
I have 20 metres at home in my garden.
我家的花园里还有条二十公尺长的水管
We can reach the cars at the end.
连最后一节车厢都能喷到
What? What?
干嘛？有那么好笑吗？
- Hujar!       - Yeah, sure.
- 胡加    - 好啊  反正好玩嘛
Don't forget the roof!
别忘了车顶
On the roof on the other side.
还有另外一边
Lieutenant, every time the train stops...
中士  每次火车停下来
...you open the doors, you give them water, yeah?
你就打开车窗给他们水  听到没？
- Okay!       - Okay!. This car! This car!
- 是的  先生    - 这节车厢
I'm not saying you'll regret it, but you might.
我不是说你一定会后悔  但是你很有可能会
- You should be aware of that.       - We will have to risk regret.
- 你们应该三思    - 我们必须承担这种风险
All right, sure. It's a nice day. I'll go for a drive with you.
好吧  看在天气不错的份上  我和你们去兜兜风
What about you?
你是为了什么进来的？
I violated the Race and Resettlement Act.
我违反了种族及再安置法令
Though I doubt anyone can point out the actual provision to me.
虽然我怀疑没人能真正指出我触犯了哪条规定
I kissed a Jewish girl.
我亲吻了一个犹太女孩
Did your prick fall off?
你的老二有没有断掉？
He likes women.
他喜欢女人
He likes good-looking women.
他喜欢好看的女人
He sees a beautiful woman, he doesn't think.
他一看到美女就没办法思考
I mean, he has so many women.
他有好多女人
And they love him.
她们都爱他
Yeah, they love him. I mean, he is married, yeah, but he's...
她们爱他  虽然他已经结婚了…
All right, no. She was Jewish. He shouldn't have done it.
好吧  她是犹太人  他不应该亲她
But you didn't see this girl.
但是你没见过这个女孩
I saw this girl. This girl was, woof...
我见过这个女孩  这个女孩…
...she was very good-looking.
她长得非常漂亮
They cast a spell on you, you know, the Jews.
你知道吗  犹太人在你身上投射了一道咒符
When you work closely with them, like I do, you see this.
你天天对着她们就会知道了
They have this power. It's like a virus. Some of my men are infected with this virus.
她们有这种能力  就像病毒  我有些部下就被感染到
They should be pitied, not punished. They should receive treatment.
我们应该同情他们  让他们接受治疗  而不是处罚他们
This is as real as typhus. I see this all the time.
就像得伤寒  常常在发生
It's a matter of money?
是不是钱的问题？
You're offering me a bribe?
你是在贿赂我？
A bribe? No. No, please. It's a gratuity.
贿赂？不是  拜托  是报答
Heil Hitler!
希特勒万岁
Hello, Amon!
你好  阿蒙
Sit down!
坐
We give you Jewish girls at five marks a day, Oskar.
我们把犹太女工借给你使用  而且一天只收你五马克
You should kiss us, not them.
你应该亲吻的是我们  而不是她们
God forbid you ever get a real taste for Jewish skirt.
千万别和犹太女人太亲热
There's no future in it. They don't have a future.
不会有结果的  她们没有未来
That's not just good, old-fashioned, Jew-hating talk.
这不只是仇恨犹太人的老调言论
It's policy now.
这已经变成全国的政策了
一九四四年四月
朱贾瓦 科卡
D部门命令葛斯少尉挖掘出并焚化一万多具
在普拉邵及克拉科夫犹太区被屠杀的犹太人尸体
Can you believe this?
你能相信吗？
As if I don't have enough to do, they come up with this?
他们好像怕我没事干  还叫我来做这个
I have to find every rag buried up here and burn it.
我必须把所有的尸体挖出来  再加以焚化
The party's over, Oskar. They're closing us down, sending everybody to Auschwitz.
这里没搞头了  他们要把所有的人送去奥斯维辛
- When?       - I don't know.
- 何时动身？ - 我不知道
As soon as I can arrange the shipments.
我一安排好就送走
Maybe 30, 40 days. That ought to be fun.
要30到40天  够我忙的
- I've been talking to Goeth.       - I know the destination.
- 我和葛斯谈过    - 我知道目的地
These are the evacuation orders.
这是撤退命令
I'm to help organize the shipments, put myself on the last train.
我负责安排好运输  再把自己放上最后一班火车
That's not what I was going to say.
我要说的不是这个
I made Goeth promise me he'll put in a good word for you.
我要他答应替你说情
Nothing bad is going to happen to you there. You'll receive special treatment.
你到那边会受到特别待遇
The directives coming in from Berlin mention "Special Treatment" more and more often.
柏林那边来的命令越来越常提到所谓的"特别待遇"
- I'd like to think that's not what you mean.       - Preferential treatment, alright?
- 你不是指那个吧？ - 说"优惠待遇"总可以了吧？
- Should we invent a whole new language?       - I think so.
- 我们一定得发明全新的用词吗？ - 我想是吧
You're staying, I take it.
我猜你是要留下来
- In Krakow? What on earth for?       - What for? You have a business to run.
- 留在克拉科夫？干嘛？ - 干嘛？你有生意要经营
Of course, you'll have to hire new workers. Poles, I guess.
没错  你是得雇用新的工人  而且是波兰工人
They cost a little more, but...
他们的工资也比较高  可是…
What are you going to do?
你又能怎么办呢？
You ran my business.
没有你的帮忙  我一个人是做不来的
No, I'm going home.
我要回老家去了
I've done what I came here for. I've got more money than any man can spend in a lifetime.
我的目标已经达到  赚的钱一辈子也花不完
Some day, this is all going to end, you know.
总有一天…这一切都会雨过天晴
I was going to say we'll have a drink then.
我本来想说到时候我们再喝一杯
I think I better have it now.
我看还是现在喝比较好
I don't understand. I mean, you want these people?
我不明白  你想要这些人？
"These people"? My people, I want my people.
他们是我的人  我想要我的人
Who are you, Moses? Come on, what is this?
你以为你是谁？摩西吗？少来了
Where's the money in this? Where's the scam?
这到底有什么好处？里头有多少油水？
It's good business.
这个大有赚头
It's good business in your opinion.
那是你个人的看法
Look, you've got to move them, the equipment, everything to Czechoslovakia.
你先得把他们和设备全迁到捷克去
Pay for all that and build another camp. Doesn't make any sense.
再花钱建一个新营房  这一点都不合理
- Look, Amon, it's good for me...       - You're not telling me something.
- 这样做对我的好处可大了    - 你有事瞒着我
I know them. I'm familiar with them. I don't have to train them.
我了解他们  不用再重新训练
- You're not telling me something.       - It's good for you. I'll compensate you.
- 那是当然的    - 你也没损失  我会补偿你
- That's right.       - It's good for the army.
- 没错    - 军队也有好处
- You know what I'm going to make?       - What?
- 知道我要制造什么吗？ - 什么？
- Artillery shells.       - Everyone is making artillery shells.
- 炮弹    - 现在大家都在搞这个
- Tank shells, they need that.       - Tanks shells, yeah!
- 那做坦克炮弹  军队很需要    - 好  坦克炮弹
- Everybody's happy.       - Everyone's happy, except me.
- 皆大欢喜    - 皆大欢喜  除了我
You're probably scamming me somehow.
你八成是在设计我
If I'm making a hundred, you've got to be making three.
如果我赚了一百马克  你铁定有赚三百马克
And if you admit to making three, then it's four actually. But how?
你要是承认  就表示其实是四百  但是怎么赚的？
- I just told you.       - You did, but you didn't.
- 我已经告诉你了    - 那肯定不是真正的理由
Yeah, all right, don't tell me.
算了  不告诉我拉倒
I'll go along with it. It's just irritating I can't work it out.
我会跟你配合  只是被蒙在鼓里让我很火大
Look, all you have to do is tell me what it's worth to you.
听我说  你只要告诉我你要多少钱
- What's a person worth to you?       - No, no, no, no.
- 你认为一条命值多少？ - 不对  不对
What's one worth to you?
是你认为值多少？
Poldek Pfefferberg, Mila Pfefferberg...
波利克•费佛柏格  蜜拉•费佛柏格
...and uh...
还有…
...uh, Stagel, Stagel...
史塔哥…
- Paul.       - Paul! Paul Stagel.
- 保罗    - 保罗•史塔哥
Doctor...
医生
- The investors. I want all of them.       - Yes, sir.
- 投资人  全部打进去    - 是的
Uh, Fischer. Ismail Fischer.
以斯曼•费雪
Fischer, Ismail.
- Josef Scharf.       - One moment, sir. I'm sorry, sir.
- 约瑟夫•夏芙    - 等一下  抱歉
Come on, Stern. Scharf, Scharf.
快点  史登  夏芙
The children, all the children!
还有小孩  所有的小孩
- Herbert Stier.       - Thank you.
- 贺伯•史迪尔    - 谢谢
- How many?       - 400, 450.
- 几个了？ - 400  450人
More, more!
继续  继续
Good morning.
早上好
- Feigenbaum, Jakob.       - Wolf. Wolf Wein.
- 雅各•费根邦      - 渥夫•维恩
Feigenbaum: Lutek, Jakob, Nacha. Yes? Nacha.
路特克  雅各  纳加
Nacha, that's right.
纳加  对了
And Wolf.
还有渥夫
How many?
几个了？
- 600.       - More!
- 六百    - 再来
You can do the same thing I'm doing.
你可以学我
- You might even make money at it.       - I don't know.
- 说不定赚得更多    - 我不知道
Come on, Julius, I know about the extra food and clothes you give them.
别这样  胡利斯  我知道你常常自掏腰包
Paid for out of your own pocket. If we make a combined approach...
给他们额外的食物和衣服  我们两个联手
...we could get more than 4,000 out, mine and yours.
可以至少救出四千人
-Oskar!       - We could relocate them in something like safety, in Moravia.
- 奥斯卡    - 把他们安置在安全的地方
I don't know.
我不知道
How many cigarettes have you smoked tonight?
你今天晚上抽了几根烟？
Too many!
记不得了
For every one you smoke, I smoke half.
你每抽一根  我就吸了半根
- I've done all I can.       - I will not accept that.
- 我已经尽力了    - 我不接受
- No, Oskar, I can't do any more.       - I will not accept that.
- 我已经没办法了    - 我绝对不接受这样的答案
No!
不
- How many? How many?       - 850, give or take.
- 多少人了？ - 大概850人
Give or take what, Stern? Count them. How many?
什么叫大概？数清楚有多少人
That's it. You can finish that page.
就这样  把那一页打完
What... did... Goeth... say about this?
这件事…葛斯怎么说？
You just told him how many people you needed and...
你只是告诉他你需要多少人  他就这么好心的…
You're not buying them?
你该不是用钱买的吧？
You're buying them? You're paying him for each of these names?
你要按人头付钱给他？
If you were still working for me, I'd expect you to talk me out of it.
要是你还帮我做事  应该要劝我不要做傻事
It's costing me a fortune.
因为这能让我倾家荡产
Finish the page and leave one space at the bottom.
把那一页打完  下面留一个空位
You...
你看
The list is an absolute good.
这份名单代表着至善
The list... is life.
这份名单…就是生命
All around its margins lies the gulf.
名单的外围是一片美丽的海湾
Oskar, there's a clerical error here at the bottom of the last page.
奥斯卡  最后一页下面多了个空格
No, there's one more name I want to put there.
没错  我要补一个名字
I'll never find a maid as well trained as her at Brinnlitz.
在我老家那很难找到像她这么专业的女佣
They are all country girls.
那里的女佣都是乡下人
No!
不行
- One hand of twenty-one.       - No!
- 赌一把21点定输赢    - 不行
- If you win, I pay you 7,400 reichsmarks.       - No!
- 你赢  我就付你7400马克    - 不行
- Hit a natural, I make it 14,800.       - No!
- 一发牌就赢  付你双倍    - 不行
If I win, the girl goes on my list.
要是我赢  就放她的名字上去
- I can't wager Helen in a card game.       - Why not?
- 我不能拿海伦当赌注    - 为什么？
Wouldn't be right.
那样是不对的
She's just going to Auschwitz Number Two, anyway.
反正她都快被送去奥斯维辛了
- What difference does it make?       - She's not going to Auschwitz.
- 有什么差别？  - 她不会的
I'd never do that to her. No, I want her to come back to Vienna with me.
我绝对不会让她去那里  我要带她一起回维也纳
I want her to come to work for me there.
我要她继续帮我做事
- I want to grow old with her.       - Are you mad?
- 我要和她白头偕老    - 你疯了吗？
- Amon, you can't take her to Vienna with you.       - No, of course I can't.
- 阿蒙  你不能带她回维也纳    - 我当然不能
That's what I'd like to do.
我只是很想那么做
What I can do, if I'm any sort of a man,
我唯一能做的是…  要是我还是个男人
is the next most merciful thing.
还有一点恻隐之心的话
I shall take her into the woods and shoot her painlessly in the back of the head.
就会带她到林子里  给她头后一枪  免得她受苦
What was it you said for a natural 21?
你说一开牌就赢给多少？
Was it 14,800?
一万四千八？
Jews of Schindler, to these tables! Say your names clearly.
辛德勒的犹太人请过去那边  把名字清楚地报出来
- We are the family Dresner.       -Juda, Jonas...
- 我们是椎斯纳一家    -  犹大 约拿斯
...Donata and Chaja.
唐娜塔和海雅
- We are Rosners. Henry, Manci...       - And Leo.
- 我们姓罗斯纳  亨利、曼希…    - 还有里奥
- And our son.       - I am Olek.
- 还有我们的儿子    - 我是欧力克
Maria Mischel.
玛利亚•米歇尔
Chaim Nowak.
汉恩•诺瓦克
Wulkan, Markus.
马可士•渥坎
Michael Lemper.
麦可•蓝伯
Itzhak Stern.
依札克•史登
Rebeka and Joseph Bau.
蕾贝卡和约瑟•包尔
- Rosalia Nussbaum.       - Wilhelm Nussbaum.
- 罗莎莉亚•奴斯班    - 威廉•奴斯班
Jakob Levartov.
雅各•李瓦图
- Farber, Rosa.       - Farber, Andrzej.
- 罗莎•法柏     - 阿吉•法柏
- Sara.       - Friehof, Fischel.
- 莎拉    - 费雪•菲何夫
Mietek Pemper.
米提克•庞贝
Poldek and Mila Pfefferberg.
波利克和蜜拉•费佛柏格
Horowitz, Dolek.
多利克•何洛维兹
Adam Levy.
亚当•李维
Marcel Goldberg.
马赛•古柏特
Klipstein, Isak David.
伊萨克•大卫•克林普斯坦
Altmann, Eduard.
艾德华•艾塔曼
Grunberg, Miriam.
蜜莉安•葛伦柏格
Luftig, Eliasz.
艾利亚斯•鲁夫提
Hilmann, Eduard.
艾德华•希尔曼
Erna Rothberg.
尔娜•罗森柏格
Zuckermann, Jetti.
约缇•祖卡曼
Helen Hirsch.
海伦•希尔施
The worst is over.
最糟的已经过去了
Men to this transport and women to this transport.
男士请上这班火车  女士请上那班火车
Be careful! Men to this transport and women to this transport.
小心一点  男士请上这班火车  女士请上那班火车
Watch your step! Men to this transport and women to this transport.
小心台阶  男士请上这班火车  女士请上那班火车
Wonderful Olek, wonderful.
做得好  欧力克  做得好
You know how we make ice into water?
你知道要怎么将冰块溶化吗？
Olek, get another one!
欧力克  再拿一根来！
捷克的祖瓦图布林兹
奥斯卡·辛德勒故乡
Position yourselves all in a single row!
所有人站成一排
You'll be pleased with the level of efficiency I get from these workers.
您将会对本劳动营的生产力非常满意
Budzyn, under my command...
在我的监督之下
...was the envy of every other commandant in the labour camp system.
我的营区是其他营区的效法目标
- The prisoners, however...       - Excuse me!
- 至于那些俘虏…    - 借过
...they would have rather been somewhere else.
则是希望能被发配到一个轻松一点的营区
The train with the women has already left Plaszow...
女士们所乘坐的火车已经离开了普拉邵
...and will be arriving here very shortly.
她们很快就会抵达这里
I know you've had a long journey.
我知道经过了长途旅行  你们都很疲倦了
But it's only a short walk further to the factory...
但是从这里到工厂只有一小段的步行距离
...where hot soup and bread is waiting for you.
在那里我已经为大家准备了热汤和面包  给大家作晚餐
Welcome to Brinnlitz!
欢迎各位来到布林兹
- Beans in chunt?       - Beans are the best part.
- 在犹太浓汤里面加豆子？ - 这样才好吃
I don't like beans.
我不喜欢豆子
Beans and meat and potatoes and bread.
豆子  肉  再加上马铃薯和面包
That's not the way you make chunt.
犹太浓汤不是这种煮法
- Eggs in chunt?       - Yes!
- 犹太浓汤加蛋？ - 对啊
- I don't like chunt.       - No, you don't.
- 我不喜欢犹太浓汤  - 你不喜欢？
- What do you like?       - I like caviar!
- 那你喜欢什么？ - 我喜欢鱼子酱
One day on the fire...
有一天…
奥斯维辛集中营
（犹太种族的"最后解决"处）
Thirty, thirty-five, forty, forty-five...
三十  三十五  四十  四十五
- Where are the list makers?       - Where are the tables?
- 怎么没有管名单的人？ - 那些桌子在哪？
Move the line!
动作快点
Mama, where are we?
妈妈  我们在哪里？
They're in Auschwitz.
她们在奥斯维辛
The train was never routed here. A paperwork mistake.
那道铁轨根本不通往这里  是作业上的错误
Take off your shoes!
脱掉鞋子
Quicker, quicker!
快点  快点
Take off your clothes! Hurry up!
快脱掉衣服
Hurry up! Stay in a row and take off your clothes!
快点  脱掉衣服站成一排
Quicker!
动作快点
快点
Take off your clothes quickly! Hurry up!
快点脱掉衣服
Go in, hurry up!
进去  快点
Quicker!
快点
Go to the showers, quickly!
快点去冲澡
Quicker! Quicker!
动作快点  快点
Eyes on the necks!
低下头！
Hands on the shoulders!
把手放在肩膀上
- How old are you, mother?       - Sixty-eight.
- 你今年几岁  太太？ - 六十八
- Cough for me, mother.       - They say to fall against the fence is a kindness.
- 麻烦咳嗽一声    - 有人说能被围墙电网电死  反而不那么痛苦
Don't kill yourself against the fence, Clara.
卡拉  千万别做傻事
If you do, you'll never know what happened to you.
留得青山在  不怕没柴烧
- How old are you, mother?       - Sixty-six, sir.
- 你今年几岁  太太？ - 六十六岁
- Sir?       - Good morning.
- 长官？  - 早安
A mistake has been made. We are not supposed to be here.
这其中恐怕有些误会  我们不该被运来这里的
We work for Oskar Schindler. We are Schindler Jews.
我们是奥斯卡•辛德勒的工人  我们是辛德勒的犹太人
- Who is Oskar Schindler?       - He had a factory in Krakow.
- 谁是奥斯卡•辛德勒？ - 他在克拉科夫有一间工厂
- Enamelware.       - A pot maker.
- 是做搪瓷器皿的    - 原来是个做锅子的人
How old are you, mother?
你今年几岁  太太？
You are not the only industrialist who needs labour...
你不是唯一一个需要劳工的工业家
...Mr. Schindler.
辛德勒先生
I remember earlier this year, IG-Color ordered...
记得今年稍早的时候
...a trainload of Hungarians for its chemical factory.
法本化学工厂跟我订了一车的匈牙利俘虏
The train came in through the archway...
火车才刚进站
...and the officer in charge of the selection went immediately to work...
那些负责筛选的军官就立刻开始工作
...and sent 2,000 of them...
他们选了两千个人
...straight away to "special treatment".
去我们的毒气室接受"特别疗程"
It is not my task to interfere with the processes that take place down here.
我对这里所发生的事根本无权干涉
Why do you think I can help you
既然我都无法帮助法本化学工厂了
if I can't help IG-Color?
你又何以认为我可以帮助你？
Allow me to express the reason.
请容许我叙述我的理由
I'm not making any judgement about you.
我并无意去评断你的人格
It's just that I know that in the coming months...
我只是知道在未来几个月
...we're all going to need portable wealth.
我们一定都会需要可以随身携带的财产
I could have you arrested.
我可以将你逮捕
I'm protected by powerful friends. You should know that.
我有许多位高权重的朋友  相信你一定知道
I do not say I am accepting them.
这并不代表我准备收下这些赠礼
All I say is, I'm not comfortable with them on the table.
我只是觉得不应该将它们摊在桌上
I have a shipment coming in tomorrow.
我明天又会有一批新货到来
I'll cut you 300 units from it.
我可以分三百个俘虏给你
New ones. These are fresh.
这些是新鲜的
The train comes, we turn it around.
火车一到  我们立刻让他们掉头
- It's yours.       - I understand.
- 让你带走    - 我了解
I want these.
可是我要的是这些人
You shouldn't get stuck on names.
你不该对这些人的名字那么执着
That's right. It creates a lot of paperwork.
这样会衍生出很多的文件处理工作
Zoldinger, Ernestina! Waldergrun, Hilda!
厄妮斯汀娜•佐丁格    海达•渥德根
Waldergrun, Leonora!
里奥诺•拉渥德根
Laast, Anna! Pfefferberg, Mila!
安娜•拉斯特    蜜拉•费佛柏格
Dresner, Ruth! Dresner, Danka!
露诗•椎斯纳    丹卡•椎斯纳
Nussbaum, Sidonia! Rosner, Manci!
希冬妮雅•奴斯班    曼希•罗斯纳
Hirsch, Helen! Grosz, Chaja Sara! Seelenfreund, Estella!
海伦•希尔施   海雅•莎拉•葛兹   丝黛拉•斯兰芳
No! No! No!
不  不要！
Hey! Hey! Hey! What are you doing?
喂  你们在干什么？
These are mine! These are my workers! They should be on my train!
她们是我的工人  她们应该要一起上火车
They're skilled munitions workers! They're essential!
她们是非常重要的弹药工人  非常重要的
Essential girls!
她们是很宝贵的女孩
Their fingers polish the insides of shell metal casings.
她们的小手指能替所有的弹壳上漆
How else am I to polish the inside of a 45 millimetre shell casing?
不然你以为我们是怎么替点四五口径的弹壳上漆的？
You tell me. You tell me!
你告诉我啊
Back on the train! Back on the train!
全都回火车上去
Under Department "W" provisions...
按照W部门的法律规定
...it is unlawful to kill a worker without just cause.
随意处决工厂工人是违法的
Under the Businesses Compensation Fund...
基于商业补偿基金的规定
...I am entitled to file damage claims for such deaths.
我可以因为这种损失而获得赔偿
If you shoot without thinking...
如果你们随意处决我的工人
...you go to prison, I get paid.
你们会去坐牢  而我可以获得赔偿
That's how it works.
就是这么回事
So, there will be no summary executions here.
所以以后这里不会再有任何就地正法的事件发生
There will be no interference of any kind with production.
也不得再有人任意来干扰我工厂的生产速度
In hopes of ensuring that, guards will no longer be allowed on the factory floor...
为了确保这一点  所有士兵除了有我的许可之外
...without my authorization.
一律禁止进入工厂
For your cooperation, you have my gratitude.
还希望各位能多多配合  我将会感激不尽
Come on, come!
来吧
Oh, boy! I haven't seen something like that since years.
我从去年就没见过这种好东西了
Come on, boys, come!
来啊  大伙儿别客气
No doorman or maitre d' will ever mistake you again...
不会再有任何门房或领班认为你不是独一无二的辛德勒夫人
...I promise.
我向你保证
Itzhak.
依札克
- This is Itzhak Stern, my accountant.       - You must be Mrs. Schindler.
- 这位是依札克•史登  我的会计    - 您一定是辛德勒夫人
- It's a pleasure to meet you.       - Emilie has volunteered to work in the clinic.
- 幸会    - 艾蜜莉将会在诊所里担任志工
- Very generous of you.       - I know.
- 你真的是太慷慨了   - 哪里
We need to talk when you have a moment.
等你有空的时候  我们可否借一步说话
This is my wife, Stern. I don't keep any secrets from my spouse.
这是我的妻子  我们之间没有任何秘密
Oskar, please, attend to business. It's much more attractive.
奥斯卡  拜托你去照顾生意吧  我对那些没有兴趣
- Madam.       - Hello!
- 夫人   - 你好
What is it?
怎么了？
We've received an angry complaint from the Armaments Board.
我们刚刚收到军备部愤怒的来电
The artillery shells, tank shells, rocket casings!
我们所生产的子弹壳  坦克及飞弹弹壳…
Apparently all of them have failed quality control tests.
全部都没有通过品管检查
That's to be expected!
这是很正常的
Start-up problems. This isn't pots and pans. This is a precise business.
初期都会这样  这可不比制造锅碗瓢盆  这是一门很精密的行业
- I'll write them a letter.       - They're withholding payment.
- 我会写信跟他们沟通    - 而且他们还拒绝付款
Sure, so would I, so would you. I wouldn't worry. We'll get it right one of these days.
那是很正常的  别担心  我们迟早会摸索出来的
There's a rumour you've been going around miscalibrating the machines.
有人谣传说你故意调乱机器的刻度
They could shut us down, send us back to Auschwitz.
这样工厂有可能会被勒令歇业  然后我们会被送去奥斯维辛
I'll call around, find out where we can buy shells.
我会去打听看看哪里有卖弹壳
- Pass them off as ours.       - I don't see the difference...
- 再去买来交货    - 我不懂这有什么不同
...whether they're made here or somewhere else.
不管是不是我们生产的…
You don't see a difference? I see a difference.
这对我来说不同
You'll lose a lot of money.
你会损失很多钱
Fewer shells will be made. Stern, if this factory ever produces...
这样会减少弹壳的产量  史登  如果我们工厂出产了
...a shell that can actually be fired, I'll be very unhappy.
任何可以被成功发射的弹壳  我会非常不高兴的
- Hello, madam.       - How do you do?
- 你好  夫人    - 你好
How are you doing, Rabbi? Rabbi!
你好吗  牧师？牧师！
Good, Mr. Director.
我很好  厂长先生
Sun's going down.
太阳快要下山了
Yes, it is.
是的
What day is this? Friday? It is Friday, isn't it?
今天星期几？星期五吗？今天是星期五  不是吗？
Is it?
是吗？
What's the matter with you? You should be preparing for the Sabbath.
你是怎么搞的？你应该去准备安息日的礼拜了
Shouldn't you?
不是吗？
I've got some wine. In my office. Come!
我的办公室里有几瓶酒  跟我来拿吧
在工厂全面开工的七个月间,辛德勒的
布林兹武器工厂从来没有制造过任何
可用的武器.
在这期间,他花了上百万马
克让他的工人维持生计并花钱打点纳粹
军官.
What?
干嘛？
Do you have any money, uh, hidden away someplace...
你是不是在哪里藏了一些钱
...that I don't know about?
是我所不知道的
No!
没有
Why? Am I broke?
怎么？我破产了吗？
Well...
这个嘛…
Yesterday morning, at 2:41 a. m...
在昨日清晨两点四十一分
...at General Eisenhower's headquarters...
裘德将军代表德国
...General Jodl...
在艾森豪将军的办公室中
...signed the Act of Unconditional Surrender...
签下了无条件投降的条约
...of all German land, sea and air forces in Europe...
并宣布德国海陆空三军
...to the Allied Expeditionary Force.
即刻由盟军军队…
And simultaneously to the Soviet High Command.
和苏联军队接管
The German war is, therefore, at an end.
德国战争就此结束
But let us not forget for a moment...
但是请诸位不要忘记…
I think it's time the guards came into the factory.
我想现在士兵可以进入工厂了
The unconditional surrender of Germany has just been announced.
德国无条件投降的事情  刚才已正式被宣布
At midnight tonight, the war is over.
在今天的午夜时分  战争正式终结
Tomorrow you'll begin the process of looking for survivors of your families.
明天你们就可以开始找寻你们幸存的亲人
In most cases, you won't find them.
对大部份人而言  结果可能是令人失望的
After six long years of murder...
在历经了六年的屠杀之后
...victims are being mourned throughout the world.
举世都在哀悼这些受难者
We've survived.
但我们存活下来了
Many of you have come up to me and thanked me.
你们当中很多人曾经亲自谢过我
Thank yourselves.
其实你们该感激的是你们自己
Thank your fearless Stern...
以及你们大无畏的史登…
...and others among you who worried about you...
还有那些在面对死亡威胁的同时
...and faced death at every moment.
仍默默照顾彼此的人
I'm a member of the Nazi party.
我是纳粹党员
I'm a munitions manufacturer.
也是一个军火制造商
I'm a profiteer of slave labour.
我还非法奴役俘虏替我做工
I am a criminal.
我现在已成为一名罪犯
At midnight you'll be free, and I'll be hunted.
在今晚午夜你们将获得自由  而我将被通缉
I shall remain with you until five minutes after midnight...
我会陪各位留在此地  直到今晚的十二时五分
...after which time, and I hope you'll forgive me I have to flee.
在那之后  请各位原谅  我必须开始逃亡
I know you have received orders from our commandant...
我知道你们的上级接到他的上级的命令
...which he has received from his superiors to dispose of the population of this camp.
要你们清除掉这个营区的所有俘虏
Now would be the time to do it.
现在是你们动手的最好时机
Here they are, they're all here. This is your opportunity.
他们全部聚集在此  这是你们的机会
Or you could leave...
或者你们可以选择离开
...and return to your families as men...
堂堂正正的回到你们家人身边
...instead of murderers.
而不要做一个杀人凶手
In memory of the countless victims among your people...
为了悼念你们无数的受难者同胞
...I ask us to observe three minutes of silence.
我希望大家能一起默哀三分钟
- Thank you, Mr. Jereth.       - Thank you, Mr. Jereth.
- 谢谢你  贾瑞斯先生    - 谢谢你  贾瑞斯先生
Open wide.
嘴巴张开
Thank you, Mr. Jereth.
谢谢你  贾瑞斯先生
Thank you, Mr. Jereth!
As soon as peace occurs, I want...
和平一旦降临  我要你…
...um, I want that cloth distributed to the workers.
我要你把布匹分给所有的工人
Two and a half metres each.
每个人分二点五尺
Also, each person is to get a bottle of vodka.
另外  也给每个人一瓶伏特加酒
They won't drink it. They know its value.
就算他们不喝  那也值几个钱
Likewise those Egipshi cigarettes we organized.
还有那些香烟  也一起分给大家
It'll be done. Everything you ask.
我会照您的吩咐去办
We've written a letter, trying to explain things...
我们写了一封信  试图解释所有的事
...in case you are captured.
如果你不幸被捕  或许会有帮助
Every worker has signed it.
每个工人都签了名
Thank you!
谢谢你
It is Hebrew, from the Talmud.
那是希伯来文  是犹太法典中的一句话
It says: "Whoever saves one life, saves the world entire. "
意思是说 "当你挽救了一条生命  你就等于挽救了全世界"
I could have got more out.
我应该可以救更多人的
I could have got more. I don't know.
我应该可以救更多人的  我也不知道
If I just...
如果我能…
I could have got more.
我或许可以救更多人
Oskar, there are 1,100 people who are alive because of you. Look at them.
奥斯卡  这1100个人都是因为你才保住了性命  看看他们
If I'd made more money...
如果我能多赚一点钱
I threw away so much money.
我浪费了很多的钱
You have no idea.
你根本无法想象
If I had just...
我若是…
There will be generations because of what you did.
因为你的善行  这些生命得以传承下去
I didn't do enough.
我做得不够
You did so much.
你已经尽力了
This car...
这辆车
...Goeth would've bought this car.
葛斯一定会愿意跟我买这台车的
Why did I keep the car? Ten people right there.
我为何要将它留下？那至少可换十条人命
Ten people.
十条人命
Ten more people.
再多救十个人
This pin...
这个别针
...two people.
两个人
This is gold.
这是纯金的
Two more people.
至少可以再换两条命
He would have given me two for it, at least one.
他会愿意用两个人做交换  至少一个
He would have given me one, one more.
他至少会再给我一个人  再多一个人
One more person.
再一条人命
A person, Stern, for this!
一个人的性命  史登  就用这个来换
I could have gotten...
我明明可以这么做的
...one more person and I didn't.
但我却没有这样做
And I, I didn't!
我没有这样做
You have been liberated by the Soviet Army!
你们已经被苏联军队解放了
Have you been in Poland?
你有去过波兰吗？
I just came from Poland.
我才刚从波兰那里过来的
Are there any Jews left?
那还有剩下任何犹太人吗？
Where should we go?
我们该往哪里去？
Don't go east, that's for sure.
千万不要往东走
They hate you there.
那里的人很仇视犹太人
I wouldn't go west either, if I were you.
如果我是你们  我也不会往西走
We could use some food.
我们需要一些食物
Isn't there a town over there?
那边不就有一个小镇吗？
Long live, Hitler!
希特勒万岁
阿蒙·葛斯被捕时正在拜得吐鲁斯的疗养院接受治疗
他后来在克拉科夫因战争中的酷行被判处反人类罪处以绞刑
德国搪瓷厂
奥斯卡·辛德勒在战后与妻子
感情失和，事业上也屡受重创.
在一九五八年，他获得耶路撒冷大屠杀纪念馆所颁赠的
正义勋章并获邀在当地的正义路种植了一棵小树
此树至今仍然在那里生长着.
■
旷野中行走的人们黑白群像渐渐变成了彩色，这是影片第一次出现了全屏的
彩色画面，阴沉了近三个小时的银屏陡然放出绚烂的光彩，象征着受尽苦难
的犹太人们来之不易的自由。影片的这处出人易料的色彩变化，体现了制作
者非凡的构思，同时带给观众们极大的艺术震撼力。
旷野中行走的人们黑白群像渐渐变成了彩色，这是影片第一次出现了全屏的
彩色画面，阴沉了近三个小时的银屏陡然放出绚烂的光彩，象征着受尽苦难
的犹太人们来之不易的自由。影片的这处出人易料的色彩变化，体现了制作
者非凡的构思，同时带给观众们极大的艺术震撼力。
今日的辛德勒犹太人
奥斯卡·辛德勒
1974年10月9日，辛德勒去世，被以天主教方式安葬在家乡的兹维塔齐尔山上，
每年都有许多许多幸存的犹太人及其后代来祭奠他的亡灵。
詹尼克·椎斯纳
丹卡·椎斯纳
莫德希·渥坎
雷萨·何洛维兹
纽希雅·何洛维兹 辛德勒在生日宴会上所亲吻的小女孩
约瑟和蕾贝卡·包尔
欧力克·罗斯纳
曼希·罗斯纳
亨利·罗斯纳
里奥·罗斯纳和他的妻子海伦
蜜拉·费佛柏格
里奥柏德·费佛柏格
依札克·史登夫人
海伦·希尔施
艾蜜莉·辛德勒夫人
今日波兰境内
只剩下四千名犹太人人口
而辛德勒犹太人的后裔
现在总计已超过六千人
谨以此片纪念当年
被屠杀的六百万名犹太人
辛德勒的名单
导 演
史蒂文·斯皮尔伯格
此片将作为电影史上永恒的光辉而存在
而史蒂文·斯皮尔伯格这个名字
也将与这部影片联系在一起而永远流传
剧 本
斯蒂文·泽里安
根据澳大利亚小说家
托马斯·科内雅雷斯
所著的同名小说改编
制 片
史蒂文·斯皮尔伯格
杰拉尔德·R·莫伦
布兰科·拉斯蒂格
连姆·尼森
本·金斯利
拉尔夫·费因斯
卡罗琳·古道
乔纳森·萨加尔
艾伯丝·戴维兹
执行制片
凯瑟琳·肯尼迪
摄 影
贾努兹·卡明斯基
电影剪辑
迈克尔·卡恩
艺术指导
艾伦·斯达斯基
配 乐
约翰·威廉姆斯
联合制片
卢·瑞文
小提琴独奏
伊扎克·帕尔曼
服装设计
安娜·毕德季卡-谢帕德
选角导演
拉克·英格兰 和 弗里茨·弗莱施哈克尔
玛格达·斯沃克巴特
托瓦·凯宾 和 李特·梅荣
朱丽叶·泰勒
制片主任   布兰科·拉斯蒂格
第一副导演   塞尔吉奥·米米卡-戈赞
第二副导演   布兰科·拉斯蒂格
助理制片
邦妮·柯蒂斯
凯伦·贝特森·卡斯贝尔
策 划
利奥波德·派戈
助理制片
欧文·高尔夫
罗伯特·雷蒙德
谨以此片献给
史蒂夫·罗斯